<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The innocent lord; or, The divine providence. Being the incomparable history of Joseph. / Written originally in French, and illustrated by the unparallel'd pen of the learned De Ceriziers, almoner to my lord the Kings brother. And now rendred into English by Sir William Lowre Knight.</title>
            <title>Joseph, ou la Providence divine. English</title>
            <author>Cerisiers, René de, 1609-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 223 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 92 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78452</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1681</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1480_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208739</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867661</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867661</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119982</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78452)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119982)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 190:E1480[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The innocent lord; or, The divine providence. Being the incomparable history of Joseph. / Written originally in French, and illustrated by the unparallel'd pen of the learned De Ceriziers, almoner to my lord the Kings brother. And now rendred into English by Sir William Lowre Knight.</title>
                  <title>Joseph, ou la Providence divine. English</title>
                  <author>Cerisiers, René de, 1609-1662.</author>
                  <author>Lower, William, Sir, 1600?-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 143, [1] p., [1] leaf of plates   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by S.G. for Charles Adams, and are to be sold at his shop at the sign of the Talbot near S. Dunstans Church in Fleetstreet.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655. [i.e. 1654]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Cerisiers, René de.  Joseph, ou la Providence divine.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb. 12. 1654"; the second 5 in the imprint date has been crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Joseph --  (Son of Jacob) --  Legends --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:119982:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119982:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:119982:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>The Innocent Lord</head>
                  <l>Who but a Joſeph could resist the dart</l>
                  <l>Of ſuch a tempting beauty, witt, and art</l>
                  <l>And haue noe fiery wound within his hart.</l>
                  <figDesc>depiction of Joseph and Potiphar's wife</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119982:2"/>
            <p>THE
INNOCENT LORD;
OR, THE
<hi>DIVINE PROVIDENCE.</hi>
BEING
The incomparable Hiſtory
OF
JOSEPH. WRITTEN
Originally in <hi>FRENCH,</hi>
and illuſtrated by the unparallel'd
Pen of the Learned <hi>De CERIZIERS,</hi>
Almoner to my Lord the Kings brother. AND
Now rendred into <hi>ENGLISH</hi>
BY
Sir <hi>WILLIAM LOWRE</hi> Knight.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>S. G.</hi> for <hi>Charles Adams,</hi> and are
to be ſold at his ſhop at the ſign of the <hi>Talbot</hi> near S. <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtans</hi>
Church in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> 165<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:119982:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119982:3"/>
            <head>THE
TRANSLATORS
APOLOGIE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen and Ladies,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou may judg me
little Souldier,
leſs Courtier,
and leaſt of all Lover, by
the order of my title in
this Dedication. I muſt
confeſs civility would
oblige me to preferre the
fairer ſex, but the Hiſtory
here diſplaies not the
<pb facs="tcp:119982:4"/>
vertues of an <hi>Innocent Lady,</hi>
but of an <hi>Innocent Lord,</hi> not
of a <hi>Genevieva,</hi> but a <hi>Joſeph;</hi>
this I hope will excuſe
me; I cannot doubt of
your judgements, and
therefore ſhall not need
many words in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half
of this work; the
ſame favour you afforded
to my former tranſlation,
I preſume cannot be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
unto this, ſince it
hath ſome advantages a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove
that, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> may juſtly
challenge a prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence;
<pb facs="tcp:119982:4"/>
the Authour is
the ſame, the frame and
impreſsion newer in the
Original, the Hiſtory Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical,
the ſeveral paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
as pleaſant and as paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate,
and the Diſcourſe
as elegant, and as full of
variety. A <hi>Romance</hi> well
penn'd, may be tolerated;
an Authentique ſtory as
well rendred, ſhould be
cheriſhed; but a Divine
Legend ought to be reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced
&amp; adored, though
in a ſimple dreſſe, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb facs="tcp:119982:5"/>
when ſo magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently
ſet forth by ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent
and ingenious an
Artiſt as <hi>de Ceriziers;</hi> if it
loſes any thing of its lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre,
I muſt impute it
wholly to my unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
Verſion; yet pardon
ſmall faults (if you meet
with any) and let my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty
obtain this privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
that you will read
it over adviſedly, and
then cenſure freely, and
ſpare not</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your humble ſervant
WIL. LOWER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:119982:5"/>
            <head>TO
MY LADY,
THE
COUNTESSE
OF
CHALAIS.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Proteſt in the firſt place, that
though <hi>I</hi> offer you this work, I
ſeek not either the effects of your
benevolence, or the protection of
your power, becauſe I feel my heart
as clear from intereſt, as I know my
ſoul exempt from fear. I have had
ſufficient good fortune, not to finde
hitherto in the addreſs of my works,
but the ſole thing which I ſought
therein, which was the honour to
<pb facs="tcp:119982:6"/>
render my teſtimony publick upon
the eſteem of ſome particular perſons.
Though it ſeems that my preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
ſhould excuſe a more mixt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention,
and the change of life that
I have made might give me thoughts
leſſe noble, I proteſt yet once again,
that I look not upon either your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,
or your benefits. I give li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty
to all the world to examine my
writings, without pretending any
ſafeguard againſt the Academy; but
I requeſt you that without conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
my offering, you would deign to
ſuffer the affection that conſecrates it
you. You ſhould not deny me this
honour, ſince it is no longer free for
me to obey you, though you your ſelf
ſhould have a will contrary to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations
which your excellent merit
gives me. Your generoſity hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented
me with ſo many favours, that
it is impoſſible for me to retain that
teſtimony of my reſentment. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
without declaring my
ſelf more openly upon the motives
<pb facs="tcp:119982:6"/>
of ſo juſt a gratitude, permit me <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi>
to ſay that one of your bounties
alone is capable to raviſh from me all
the heart that I have, and to raviſh it
from me everlaſtingly. You have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired
to know me in a conjuncture,
wherein many perſons, whom I belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
to have gained either by my ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
or by their promiſes, have feign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
not to know me. You apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
not that my misfortune was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious,
nor that my miſery might be
troubleſome to you: Your courage
extended it ſelf unto me even in an
eſtate, which rejecteth very often the
moſt generous courteſies. In which
to ſpeak the truth, you have done that
which belongs not but to the greateſt
ſouls, who never withdraw themſelves
from an unfortunate party, provided
that he be innocent. Though I ſhould
not love that little vertue which you
ſuppoſe in me, your judgement would
ſollicit me to be amorous of it; inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much,
<hi>Madam,</hi> that I have you the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation
not only to believe me, but
<pb facs="tcp:119982:7"/>
alſo to render me vertuous. Certainly
if beauty be the glory of bounty, (as
<hi>Plato</hi> will have it) I judge by that lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable
profuſion, which you have u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
in my behalf, that yours how per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
ſoever it be, is unfaithful, ſince it
ſheweth not upon your viſage all the
treaſure of your ſoul; and that you
are much better, then you appear
fair. I hope from the mercy of God
(notwithſtanding any croſſe that may
come unto me from fortune) that he
will continue me the good motions,
which his Grace inſpires me; and
that for the favourable thoughts,
which you have of them, he will give
me the means to publiſh to all the
world the juſt cauſe that I have to
be all my life,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt humble,
and moſt obedient ſervant
De CERIZIERS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:119982:7"/>
            <head>TO THE
READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Pretend not to make thee a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face
greater then my Book;
there needs but a word or
two to ſay unto thee, that
this Patriarch is but one of
the Infants of my wit, and that thou ought<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
to ſee the others, if thou cheriſheſt the
true Hiſtory. I promiſe thee not all
thoſe whom God promiſeth to his ſervant
<hi>Abraham,</hi> thou wouldſt have then more
cauſe to fear then to hope, becauſe I
ſhould be leſſe obliging then troubleſome.
Expect all thoſe whom thou deſireſt, ſince
I am reſolved to give thee as many of them
as thou wilt receive: I will not ſtop my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign
but where thou ſhalt bound thy deſire.
Thou ſhalt finde a ſtyle more extended then
<pb facs="tcp:119982:8"/>
in my reflections; but thou wilt judge alſo
that if the Diſcourſe requires ſinew and
point, the ingenuity and the words apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
to the Hiſtory. I husband thee my
wit following the nature of the ſubjects
which I handle, deny me not neither thy
attention, nor thy patience. I perſwade
me that thou wilt not have the ſcruple of
thoſe, who give all the force and goodneſſe
of their thoughts to the robe and profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
of their Authour; as if the dew of
Heaven falls not but upon the mountains,
and the depth of the valleys were deprived
of that ſweet influence. It would not be
without ingratitude, if I ſhould deny that
little capacity which I have, to the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
which hath bred me; but it would be
ſottiſhneſſe to believe that I ſhould have
left there my reaſon, being obliged to come
forth from thence. This misfortune might
be feared of a perſon, who ſhould not have
had piety for a motive of his change; for
my part, I expect recompence for it rather
then puniſhments. Thoſe who know me,
will judge, that I have not acted but by
good principles. One ſhould judge unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily
<pb facs="tcp:119982:8"/>
of the courage of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> to believe
that the perſecution of his brothers, or the
ambition of greatneſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> had conducted him
into <hi>Egypt.</hi> The onely neceſſity to nouriſh
his Father, whom the Providence of God
had rendred poor, obliged him to quit the
land of Promiſe. I adore that Providence,
which hath charged me with the ſame duty,
and I conjure it, if it be for my good, and
its glory, to clear the truth thereof. I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon
without trouble my fortune to a
goodneſſe, to which I referre willingly the
cares of my ſalvation: Saint <hi>Paul</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits
the wiſe to judge of all things, I have
no mind to limit their power: What ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity
ſoever they uſe in my behalf, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
their judgement without diſtruſting
their juſtice. For thoſe who have not recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
the ſame Authority of the Apoſtle,
and of their prudence, I as little ſeek their
approbation, as I fear their cenſure.
Thanks unto God, all thoſe that judge are
not of the Parliament; one may mock at
their prate, if they cannot defend it. As
I deſpiſe generouſly the liberty of fools, who
make themſelves arbiters of the moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant
<pb facs="tcp:119982:9"/>
affairs of the world, I reverence
with ſubmiſſion the examen of thoſe that
reſemble thee. But if this ſhort Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
renders me not worthy of thy eſteem,
and that thy curioſity cannot be ſatisfied
from my own teſtimony, addreſſe thee to
the <hi>R. R. P. P. Jaquinot, le Cazre,</hi>
Saint <hi>Mary, Marquenat, Dagonel</hi> and
<hi>Ricueil;</hi> I aſſure me that thou wilt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand
from them that I have done
without crime, what I think I ought to
doe in conſcience. I have received too
much honour in their company to fly it, I
have lived innocently enough to abide
there: my departure is the tyranny of an
indiſpenſable neceſſity, and not the humour
of a ridiculous inconſtancy. But if I have
not found in Religion a ſuccour which I
ſeek in the world, aſſure thy ſelf that
ſome other reaſon then my defects, hath
hindred the effect of the moſt ardent of my
deſires. After the ſuffrage of theſe great
men which I have obſerved, becauſe they
have examined my change, I aſſure me that
no body will condemn it, but thoſe who have
neither the intereſts of Fathers or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb facs="tcp:119982:9"/>
nor the ſenſe of true children. My
dear Reader, attend the reſt of my Apology,
from that which remains of my life; the
honour which I ſhall endeavour to conſerve
me amongſt good men, ſhall lay the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation
of all the praiſe that I pretend
from thy good will. I tell thee this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
I deſire to keep me in thy memory,
proteſting that I ſhould be very ſorry that
my ſtyle ſhould pleaſe thee, if my conduct
might diſpleaſe thee.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:119982:10"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119982:10"/>
            <head>JOSEPH,
OR, THE
DIVINE PROVIDENCE.</head>
            <p>NEver ſaw <hi>Egypt</hi> a fairer day, then that
which began the glory of <hi>Joſeph:</hi> the
Heaven communicated new lights
to illuſtrate the apparel of his triumph;
and the Earth ſeemed to paint her ſelf to appear
beauteous to the eyes of this new God. The trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets
made ſo pleaſing a noiſe, that all the houſes
became ſo many Eccho's to repeat it. The tape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtries
were no more the ornament of the walls,
but the litter of the horſes, which trampled up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
indifferently both the purple and the ſilk; it
would be hard to finde all the Mines of Gold,
which ſhone in the ſtreets of that proud City;
the pearles and diamonds paſſed for common
ſtones. What need I ſay that the <hi>Heroes</hi> and
ſouldiers were cloathed with cloth of gold
and cloth of ſilver, the beaſts of charge and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lephants
being covered therewith, would not
leave that advantage unto man; the Princes of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119982:11"/>
the Court were ſo glorious, and ſo proudly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned,
that without appearance of deceit,
they might have been taken for Kings. One
would have thought that the Ladies had bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed
other viſages then their ordinary ones;
all was changed, whileſt our ſlave led the heart
of <hi>Pharoah</hi> in triumph. This ſpectacle had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
in it of low, as no body had mean exta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies.
But perhaps the glory of ſo magnifick a
pomp rather wearies your eyes, then recreates
them; and to conſider longer theſe marvels,
would but augment your trouble. The Sun is
alwayes fair, notwithſtanding one hath often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
more pleaſure to ſee him riſe on the top of
a mountain, then to admire him in his Meridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an;
becauſe his firſt raies ſuffer themſelves to be
look'd upon, whereas it ſeems that that great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe
of light, with which he is gloriouſly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſſed,
is but to hide him from our eyes, or
to puniſh our curioſity. Perhaps the Infancy
of our Patriarch will pleaſe you no leſſe then
his perfect age, and his firſt vertues then his full
perfection: and as there is an all-particular
Providence that made him paſſe from contempt
unto glory, ſo I would fain make him appear mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable
at firſt, to the end that you may conſider
him with more pleaſure in the happineſſe of his
fortune.</p>
            <p>It was in the fourteenth year of <hi>Jacobs</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,
that <hi>Rachel</hi> was mother of another child,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119982:11"/>
then that of her ſervant <hi>Bilhah,</hi> and ſaw her ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
payed for all her prayers, wherewith ſhe impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuned
Heaven. This childe-bed made her
more happy, though leſſe fruitful then her ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,
foraſmuch as ſhee poſſeſſed more in this
onely ſon, then <hi>Leah</hi> had in all hers. If the
benefits of Grace ſurpaſſed not infinitely thoſe
of nature, it would be hard to judge which of
the two had been more liberal to him; and
without doing wrong to the one or the other,
it might have been ſaid that he had all the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues
of his father, and the beauty of his mother.
So many graces perfectionated his body, that
all which could have been wiſh'd him, was no
more the object of a reaſonable deſire. Often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
the neighbours would come unto the
houſe of <hi>Laban,</hi> to ſee onely his viſage, (which
diſſipated the blackeſt ſorrowes) and to carry
unto their houſe the contentment which they
fonnd in his company.</p>
            <p>That which moſt powerfully raviſheth hearts,
hath a luſtre more glorious then that of the
colour, and is fixed to ſomething more noble
then the body. An Ancient ſaith, that beauty
is the facility of the eyes, though to ſpeak pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly,
it is ordinarily but the ruine of ſouls, or
at beſt but the perfection of women. Our lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
Infant had other attractions, ſince he poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
that beauty, which is not beloved, but of
pure ſouls, and of him who glories to be the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119982:12"/>
Spouſe of them: It is true, that his age ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
not yet to be that of vertue; notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
it appeared ſo viſibly on his viſage, and
in all his actions, that one might think it was
a part of that ſpirit which animated them, or
if it were any thing ſeparate, that it was rather
born with him, then gotten by the cuſtome of
practiſing it: above all, there was ſeen ſo rare
a modeſty in him, that all his companions
could correct themſelves by his example, and
regulate themſelves by his conduct. It was ſhe
that opened, and that ſhut his eyes; it was ſhee
that made him ſpeak by civility, and be ſilent
by diſcretion: it was ſhe that counted his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
and that compos'd his countenance: it
was ſhe that governed him ſo abſolutely, that
he never offended the meaneſt of the ſervants,
not ſo much as with one word ſpoken in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt,
or eſcaped by precipitation; this good
quality rendred him amiable unto men, and his
piety unto God. Never roſe he, or went to
bed, but he made his little devotions, and
though he could ſcarce pronounce the name of
God, he adored the Majeſty of him. It was a
pleaſure which drew tears of joy from his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
and mother, to ſee him pray with ſo good
a grace; and to ſpeak truth, even thoſe who
had no intereſt in his good inclinations, would
be troubled not to pleaſe him. Who could
behold without raviſhment, a childe of five
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119982:12"/>
or ſix years to adore God with an affection ſo
inſtant and recollected, as if he had had no i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magination,
or that his imagination had been
determined to this onely action? To ſee him
on his knees, his hands joyned, his eyes halfe
ſhut, one would have thought that it was a
ſtatue of marble, if thoſe lips had not given
ſome motion to his prayer, or an Angel, if he
had not ſighed ſometimes. I ſpeak not of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence
with which he honoured his parents;
the belief thereof is eaſie through the ſweetneſs
that rendred him pleaſing to all the world.
One might produce many proofs thereof, but
it ſufficeth me to aſſure that there was no cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler
ſo kindled, nor rage ſo fierce that would not
be changed in his preſence. <hi>Jacob</hi> knew it well;
this good Patriarch vexed with ſorrowes,
which for twenty years had not ſuffered him
to breath; beſides, believing to have bought
two wives, and ſome ſheep too dear, reſolved
to take his leave, ſince that his father in law
refuſed him. Behold then this holy man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained
to cover himſelf with the ſame dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
that Thieves and Robbers hide themſelves
under: hee departed in the night with his
Train, for fear the brightneſſe of the day
might publiſh that which he would keep ſecret,
(I leave that which arrived during this flight
to <hi>Laban,</hi> as not belonging to my ſubject; this
man which was to wreſtle with God, feared
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119982:13"/>
the encounter of a brother, whom his vertues
had made an enemy to him. His former mena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
that fury, which rendred him more ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vage
then a Bear, the hair with which he was
covered, gave him more fear of his hate, then
blood and nature aſſurance of his love.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding chuſing rather to hazard
once his life, then to lead it alwayes in ſo pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
labours, he fixed himſelf to his firſt deſign,
from which all the conſiderations that he had,
could not divert him. After having thought
of the means of his reconciliation, the cruelty
of <hi>Eſau</hi> ſeemed not unto him an invincible
paſſion. That thought which hee approved
moſt of all upon this ſubject, was to divide his
Train into two Bands, and to ſend them ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively
to the encounter of his brother: but
the ſecret of the Artifice was to put <hi>Joſeph</hi> and
his mother in the laſt, to the end that their
beauty mingled with the ſweetneſſe of ſo piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
a ſpectacle, might change the heart of this
barbarous man, if the maſſacre of thoſe that
preceded it, nor the conſideration of blood
had not ſtopped his fury.</p>
            <p>I know not what Magick an innocent beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
uſeth, but we ſee the effects as admirable, as
the cauſes thereof are ſecret and little known:
how many times have we ſeen Tyrants become
Idolaters of thoſe whom they perſecuted, and
take the ſubject of their love, from whence
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119982:13"/>
they drew the motive of their hate? The Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers
themſelves, and the Panthers, have they
not quitted their nature, to take ſweeter ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
then is neceſſary to devour innocents?
The Lions and the Leopards have rendred
them homage, humbling their cruelty before
thoſe whom they thought to devour: they
have adored their victime, and their prey; the
artifice of <hi>Jacob</hi> was not then evil, ſince hee
endevoured to take his brother by that which
gained the moſt ſavage beaſts. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
God diſpoſed thereof otherwiſe, and
becauſe he would not divide with any one the
acknowledgement of that benefit, he would
that he ſhould owe all the obligation thereof to
his goodneſſe. <hi>Eſau</hi> becomes man, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives
him with careſſes, who expected nought
from him but perſecutions. It was at the ſight
of this happy <hi>Canaan,</hi> that <hi>Jacob</hi> ſeemed to
live another life then that which he led in <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopotomia;</hi>
and though two great Rivers give it
its name and fecundity, that land notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
appeared unto him more faire and
more fertile then that where appeared the firſt
Paradiſe of man. The joy to have no more
<hi>Eſau,</hi> the hope to embrace the good <hi>Iſaak,</hi>
gave ſo ſweet ſallies to his heart, that hee
thought he ſhould have need of ſome misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune,
to moderate his joy. Whileſt that they
travelled towards <hi>Hebron,</hi> they perceived a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119982:14"/>
Town ſituated on the browe of an Hill,
which defended it from the North. Our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch
no ſooner ſaw it, but he commanded
all his people to put themſelves on their knees,
which he firſt did himſelf, to give them exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
of obedience. This command could not
be without reaſon, coming from ſo wiſe a
man. Notwithſtanding, <hi>Rahel</hi> took the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty
to ask it him, which obliged him to tell
them, that it was the place where the <hi>Meſſias</hi>
ſhould take birth, and begin that which God
onely could finiſh. Alas, how difficult is it
for proſperity to laſt long, and how hard to
finde a happineſſe conſtant out of that reſidence
which is to be eternal? <hi>Jacob</hi> began to be no
more miſerable, when the moſt ſenſible of all
his afflictions arrived unto him, it was the death
of his poor <hi>Rahel,</hi> who could not give life to
her <hi>Benoni</hi> without loſing it her ſelf. I leave
the regrets and the tears, which followed her
death; but I cannot paſſe in ſilence an action
that preceded it, ſince it touched <hi>Joſeph.</hi> His
good mother ſeeing that her life would hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth
advantage him nothing, deſired that the
laſt moments thereof ſhould be uſeful unto him:
Having then cauſed him to come to her, ſhee
leaned upon his boſome, and moiſtening his
viſage with her tears, ſhe ſpake unto him in
this manner.</p>
            <p>My ſon, I cannot die without bidding you
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119982:14"/>
adieu, and wiſhing you a bleſſing, which I
beſeech the will of Heaven to accompliſh. I
am in a condition, where intereſt makes no
body ſpeak; therefore if I leave you any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,
I ſuppoſe you will not believe that any
conſideration of mine comes to mingle there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
I have alwayes as much loved your vertue
and good inclinations, as your perſon; it is
therefore I deſire you but ſo much life, as they
ſhall laſt. It is not the fear of your inconſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,
that makes me ſpeak in this manner, but
the ardent deſire which I have of your perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.
Make then your vertue to grow with
your age, and never think to have enough of
thoſe goods, whoſe abundance can make no
exceſſe: Let the ſervice of our great God bee
your principal occupation; be never wanting
to the reſpect which you owe to your good
father; and if you owe any thing unto her
from whom you derive your birth, know,
that I transferre all the right thereof unto him,
to the end to augment your reſpects and your
ſervices. You have a great number of bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
let love tye you more unto them then
nature, and let the honour which you beare
them be a mark of your good will. Never
give their actions an ill interpretation, and if
any one of yours diſpleaſe them, endevour to
amend it. Keep alwayes your ſpirit prepared
for injuries which you may receive; perhaps
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119982:15"/>
this advice of mine is not unſeaſonable: Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
ſo perfect a reſemblance with your father,
I fear that you ſhould reſemble him alſo in this.
The affliction of the younger brothers is one
of the inheritances of your houſe; the ſon of
<hi>Hagar</hi> could not endure the ſon of <hi>Sarah; E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau</hi>
perſecuted your father in the belly of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becca;</hi>
take heed that the ſame happen not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
you; but if God permit it, think that
your affliction ſhall be rather a teſtimony of his
love, then an effect of his hate. Adieu my
dear ſonne, and retain the laſt words of your
poor mother.</p>
            <p>There is nothing more true then this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,
which will that an innocent life ends
alwayes with an happy death. <hi>Rahel</hi> had
ſcarce ended the laſt word of thoſe which ſhee
left to her ſon, but ſhe ceaſed to live, with ſo
much conſtancy that it was eaſie to judge, that
the faireſt face of the world, feared not that
which is eſteemed the moſt ugly. But certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
if her courage ſhewed the contempt of her
death, the tears of her friends witneſſed enough
how precious her life was to them. The poor
<hi>Joſeph,</hi> who had received the ſoul of his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
upon his lips, remained long time in a
ſound upon her body; and as their embrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
had ſtraitly united them, one would
have believed that death not able neither to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate
them, nor chuſe them, had not offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119982:15"/>
the mother without hurting the ſon. O
how happy had he been, if that death had
dured more then a quarter of an hower, ſince
he muſt not live longer but to ſuffer, nor ſuffer
but to inſtruct himſelf from the experience of
his meaner evils, how he ſhould prepare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
for the miſeries of ſlavery. Let us not
engage us in the regrets of this deſolate fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly;
the ſilence of great griefs makes them bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
comprehended, then the Diſcourſe that one
endevours to make thereof; the eloquence of
a few ſighs is ſtronger then that of many
words. <hi>Jacob</hi> had never ſo much trouble as
to leave that which reſted to him of his dear
wife; notwithſtanding he muſt quit it, <hi>and
receive for conſolation the confidence to be more
aided by her interceſſion, then by her preſence.</hi>
And then being perfectly ſubmitted to the
will of Heaven, he conſented that it ſhould
enrich it ſelf with the moſt precious of his
loſſes, and that it ſhould encreaſe its felicities
with his miſeries. Theſe conſiderations, and
time having given ſome comfort to his grief,
he continued his way towards <hi>Hebron,</hi> where
he was no ſooner arrived, but the good <hi>Iſaak</hi>
ran to meet him; (if to goe ſo faſt as one can
may be ſaid to run) What pen is capable to
deſcribe the careſſes, which were ſweet enough
to leave no more bitterneſſe in the heart of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi>
and to blot out the remembrance of 20.
years travels?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:119982:16"/>
All the children of this holy Patriarch par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipated
of this encounter, but <hi>Joſeph</hi> took
the greateſt part thereof; there was not one
of them that admired not the Majeſty of that
Venerable old man, who had never been ſo, if
the Angel had permitted him to obey entirely,
and if God had not loved him better for of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering,
then for victime.</p>
            <p>Some days being paſſed away in feaſts and
rejoycings, every one reſumed the cares of
good Husbandry. <hi>Iſaak</hi> was very glad to ſee
that idleneſſe never found his nephewes at lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,
and that their diligence received not ſuch
ſoft temptations as thoſe of ſloth; but his joy
was perfect, when he obſerved in <hi>Joſeph</hi> that
couragious vertue, which had almoſt made
him the Martyr of <hi>Abraham,</hi> though <hi>Abraham</hi>
ſhould not be the Tyrant of <hi>Iſaak;</hi> and to
ſay true, it was a thing very conſiderable to
ſee with what attention this little innocent ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died
the deſires of his parents, and how care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
he was to know their inclination. Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes
his obedience prevented their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,
for fear they might have the trouble to
ſpeak, and hee the blame to know their will
without accompliſhing it. The difficulty
rendred his obedience more ready, and if he
found excuſes, it was to cover the imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of another, and not to flatter his negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:119982:16"/>
All thoſe that ſaw him without envy, ſaw
him with love. The father who had long
time diſſembled his contentment, reſolved to
give him teſtimonies thereof, and to make them
appear with more luſtre, he cauſed a melley
coat to be made him, where the blue, the carna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
the white, and the other colours, were
ſo perfectly mingled, that every one could
judge that art hath thoſe beauties which ſurpaſs
the natural. Infancy pleaſeth it ſelf more with
that which ſhineth, then with that which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteth.
Our young man held yet of that age;
ſo ware he not this coat but with the ſallies of
an innocent joy, but too ſimple: poor child,
you know not that to cover you with this coat,
was to charge you with the hatred of your
brethren, and that the love of your father
ſhould be the chief cauſe of your misfortunes.
This favour was ſo grievous to the eyes of the
other children of <hi>Jacob,</hi> that they could not
long diſſemble their diſpleaſure. Nothing
was heard but plaints and murmures in their
houſe; ſome of them were bold enough to
ſay, that he loved this minion like a Legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate,
and his eldeſt like Baſtards; it was not
hard to fore-ſee the evil conſequence which ſo
many ill words promiſed. <hi>Iſaak<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> blinde as
he was, ſaw it well, and to bring ſome ſweet
remedy to this evil, he was of opinion that <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi>
ſhould withdraw himſelf for ſome days
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119982:17"/>
from the preſence of his brethren; this coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel
was thought good, and the means to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute
it eaſie.</p>
            <p>It was ſuppoſed that the children of <hi>Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hah,</hi>
and of <hi>Zilpah,</hi> would ſuffer <hi>Joſoph</hi> more
willingly, then thoſe of <hi>Leah,</hi> who knew too
well the advantages of their birth. Behold
him then made a Shepherd as well as his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren;
the innocence of this life gave him ſuch
perfect joyes, that he would ſcarce change his
ſheep-hook for a Kings Scepter: The ſenſe of
theſe delights made him believe that he had
not lived until then; and that to amuſe him
in his fathers houſe, they had made him to ſee
the pictures of that which he had before his
eyes in the fields. The Meadowes produced
him not more flowers then pleaſures; it was
from thence that he took occaſion to admire
the rare perfections of God, and to ſay unto
him in the exceſſes of his devotion, Oh my
God, how fair art thou! ſince that a little
Tract of thy incomparable beauty can make us
to love the Earth. How rich art thou! ſince
thou draweſt ſuch precious treaſures from the
dirt.</p>
            <p>There was by this Meadow a Wood, where
many Brooks ſeemed to take pleaſure to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
in the ſhade; at leaſt their flight was ſo
ſlow, that the eye could ſcarce judge from
whence they came; and whether the ſame
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119982:17"/>
roots which fixed the poplars in this pleaſant
abode, did not retain them here alſo. Every
day a great number of Birds invited our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtour
to ſeek there the freſh; and very often
the heat of the mid-day conſtrained him to goe
thither, though the ſweetneſſe of this Muſick
had not allured him. This ſolitude pleaſed
him infinitely, becauſe he had means to ſigh
there at his pleaſure, and to ſend a thouſand
times a day his heart into Heaven. I believe
that he had taken root in this Wood, if ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity
had not ſometimes diverted him thence,
and if he had not taken pleaſure to wander up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
the bank of that fountain, which was the
mother of ſo many rivulets, and the ſource of
ſo many pleaſures.</p>
            <p>It was there that he purified his ſoul, not
with the waters of the Fountain, but rather
with the tears of Devotion, which he ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
therein. After having paſſed a part of the
day to ſee the Trees and the Birds to ſwim in
this water, he remained the Evening upon its
Banks to conſider the Stars, which ſeemed to
deſcend from Heaven to bathe themſelves
there. But <hi>Joſeph</hi> had nobler thoughts, and
though his diſcretion would conceal them
carefully, the exceſſe of his love made it break
forth without deſigne. My God, (cryed he)
that I have not a ſoul ſo diſpoſed to receive
the impreſſion of thy holy graces, as this water
<pb facs="tcp:119982:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:119982:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:119982:19"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:119982:19"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:119982:20"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:119982:20"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:119982:21"/>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119982:21"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:119982:22"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:119982:22"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:119982:23"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:119982:23"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:119982:24"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:119982:24"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:119982:25"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:119982:25"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:119982:26"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:119982:26"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:119982:27"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:119982:27"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:119982:28"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:119982:28"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:119982:29"/>
entertains the image of all the objects that
preſent themſelves there? And then taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother
cogitation, he ſaid, Thou wilt then,
Love of my ſoul, thou wilt give me the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtes
of the Beatitude, which thou prepareſt
for me in Heaven: I march already upon the
Stars, and I have under my feet that which
ſhines over my head; is it not to teach me
the contempt, and the innocent hate of the
faireſt things, to the end not to love but that,
without which nothing is fair? If it be thy
deſigne, it is my deſire; if it be thy will, I
conſent thereunto, and embrace it, ſo much
the more willingly, as this inclination is
conformable to my duty. His thoughts were
yet better then the words with which he ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured
to expreſſe them.</p>
            <p>Thirty days ſlid away in a life ſo full of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights,
when an unlucky accident came to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupt
the courſe thereof. <hi>Joſeph</hi> having ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
one day too long in the Sun, whoſe heats
were then exceſſive, returned home with a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent
Feaver; his brothers fearing, if more evil
ſhould happen, that their father would ſuſpect
them of ſome malice, or at leaſt would blame
them of negligence, would ſend him to <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brou,</hi>
the moſt conveniently that it was poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.
If <hi>Jacob</hi> was ſick with this dear childe, I
muſt leave the judgement thereof to thoſe who
have, and who love children: So it was that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119982:29"/>
the good care which was uſed to procure him
health, put him ſoon out of danger, and his
father out of apprehenſion. The joy of this
recovery was not long, foraſmuch as <hi>Joſeph</hi>
having diſcovered a crime, which muſt not
have name in the Hiſtory, ſince it hath no or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
in nature, his brothers kindled the more
their hatred againſt his vertue: To make
him feel ſome effect thereof, they formed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
him the moſt blackeſt &amp; ſottiſh calumny
that could be imagined. The good opinion w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi>
               <hi>Jacob</hi> had of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> was an ill diſpoſition to
the ſucceſſe of their deſign. Notwithſtanding
he muſt hear all that which rage would vomit
forth of unjuſt againſt the vertue of this Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent.
One told him that it was no marvel if
this minion drew all his good will to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice
of thoſe that ſhould divide it with him,
ſince it was an effect of his Magick, and not of
his merit: that the familiarity which he had
with the Devils was not to be doubted, ſince his
prudence had taken ſo little care to cover it,
that an whole Province could know it. For
my part, (ſaid one of them) I have often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
ſeen him ſpeak to the Moon, and make
the Trees change place: Another aſſured,
that he ſurpriſed him in the Wood, where
he made an infinity of tears with a rod, with
which he drew the ſouls from Hell: A third
ſwore that he had made him ſee upon the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurface
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119982:30"/>
of the water, and in the nails the ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
of all that which he deſired. There was
not one of them that indeavoured not to tell
ſome fair lye, and to give evil impreſſions of
him whoſe vertue was odious unto them. But
certainly their malice and his innocence rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
the faith of this calumny, in augmenting
rather his glory, then furthering his contempt.
Slander is very impudent, yet not enough ſo as
to look upon a face without ſhame, which it
indevours to ſully without cauſe. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was
abſent when his brothers repreſented him in
ſuch evil colours; nothing rendred their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice
more bold, then the pretext that they took
of his piety, and of the devotions which he
practis'd. Behold an accident that ſeemed to
aid their intention, and give ſome ſhadow of
truth to that which could not have the light
thereof.</p>
            <p>A few dayes after <hi>Jacob</hi> invited his children
to his Table, to the end to finde the means to
reconcile them in that common rejoycement;
but he conſidered not how farre their hatred
went, and that envy is not pacified, whileſt ſhe
ſees proſperity, where ſhe wiſhes nothing but
miſerie.</p>
            <p>After many diſcourſes, ſome one having ſet
forth that oftentimes ſleep repreſents us things,
the event whereof is conformable to the Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
that one hath had thereof. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> taking
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119982:30"/>
the word, began a diſcourſe which ended not
with the approbation of all the company; for
though it was innocent, it was not pleaſing.</p>
            <p>My brethren, (ſaid he) ſince the occaſion
preſents it ſelf, give me leave to recount unto
you two or three of my dreams, and be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
to hear the pleaſant imaginations that I
have had ſome days ſince; it ſeemed unto me
one of thoſe nights, that we were in a great
Plain, covered with the richeſt Harveſt that one
could deſire, and that each of us having bound
a ſheaf, yours encompaſſed mine round about,
and did reverence unto it. Never had I a
more pleaſing illuſion then this, becauſe you
would have ſaid to ſee them, that they had
reaſon ſo to doe, and that my ſheaf was the
Queen of all the others.</p>
            <p>Some days after I had another dream,
which puts me upon the hazard to be thought
fooliſh in my ſleep; for me thought t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at the
Sun, the Moon, and eleven of the moſt glit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering
Stars fell from Heaven, and proſtrated
themſelves before me: their brightneſſe ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
to be obſcured in my preſence, as if the
glory of my viſage had had the power to do
to all thoſe lights, what the greateſt of all the
Stars cauſeth to be done to the leſſer, with this
difference, notwithſtanding that the Stars hide
themſelves for fear to court the Sun, whereas
the obſcurement of their raies was an humble
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119982:31"/>
homage which they rendered me. Whileſt
our young man related that which he had ſeen
in his ſleep, there was not one of his brothers
that hoped not but their calumny ſhould be
propped with theſe dreams. It was all the
fruit which they gathered from theſe ſheaves,
and the only brightneſſe which they drew from
that Sun. But as <hi>Simeon</hi> made reflexion upon
that which theſe dreams might ſignifie, he
cryed out with a voice that made ſufficiently
appear his evil heart. Perhaps we ſhall be your
ſervants; his furious looks made up the reſt of
his diſcourſe. The poor father, who ſaw his
indeavour ſucceed contrary to his intention,
and who penetrated enough into the myſteries
of thoſe viſions, judged it fit to diſlike them
in apparence, to the end to content thoſe, who
held themſelves offended therewith.</p>
            <p>You may be aſhamed, <hi>Joſeph,</hi> to relate
theſe fooleries with ſo much complaiſance, as
if they were true Hiſtories. Do you not bluſh
to have an imagination that makes the ſheaves
to go, and the Stars to dance? You ſhould
have concealed, if you had been wiſe, a thing
which cannot bring you but confuſion and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy;
and then turning himſelf towards the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers:
you have no reaſon to expound ſo ill
the dreams of a childe; do you not ſee that
there is no apparence to give the ſenſe as you
interpret them; if they were reaſonable, I
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119982:31"/>
ſhould have the ſame intereſt as you. For if
you are the Stars, I am your Sun, and if I am
a Sun, is not <hi>Rabel</hi> that Moon which eclipſes
my lights, ſince ſhe hath loſt all hers? But
alas, her ſorrowful death hinders her much to
increaſe, and to advance the glory of her miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
ſon. This ſweet remembrance drew ſo
many tears from the eyes of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and molli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
ſo his heart, that compaſſion changed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
the hearts of his children, and made them
forget their murmure. Let us not buſie our
ſelves to deſcribe the artifices which this good
father imployed to ſettle peace in his houſe.
When he ſpake to his eldeſt, he pick'd out his
faireſt words wherewith to ſweeten their exaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration:
On the contrary, he compoſed
himſelf with ſo much ſeverity for the innocent
<hi>Joſeph,</hi> that his brethren believed eaſily his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace.
This policy having taken away or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhed
their envy, all went happily enough;
but <hi>Jacob</hi> deſiring that this good correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
might not be for a day, prayed his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
to go to <hi>Sichem,</hi> to the end to withdraw
them from the occaſions of contention. The
neceſſity of affairs was the pretence of this voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age,
though this deſire was the true cauſe
thereof. Some time after their departure, he
judged it expedient that <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſhould viſit
them, for fear that they ſhould take ſuſpition
of their remove, and that they might not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119982:32"/>
that this Favourite was only kept at
home with their Father to receive his Careſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
with more ſafety. This reſolution being
ſetled, he commanded him to chuſe fruits, and
comfitures to carry to his brethren. There is
I know not what prudence in us that ſeems to
fore-ſee, and advertiſe us of our ill fortunes:
<hi>Joſeph</hi> found no difficulty in this obedience;
notwithſtanding he repreſented in his ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
ſimplicity, that the night paſs'd, he belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
to have ſeen ſeven or eight Wolves, which
purſued a Lamb, whoſe ruine had been certain
had not a generous Lion undertaken its defence
and ſcattered them. This viſion made the good
Patriarch weigh the deſign of ſending his ſon
to <hi>Sichem,</hi> notwithſtanding the reſcue of that
Lion aſſured him: and then he judged not
fit to take all the dreams of a child for myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.
Beh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld then our little Shepherd, who
diſpoſed himſelf to go towards his brethren,
and who bid adieu to thoſe of the houſe: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove
all he embraced his poor father ſo ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
that he could ſcarce ſeparate himſelf from
him; he received his bleſſing with ſuch ſweet
tears, that the ſenſe thereof paſſed even to the
heart of <hi>Jacob.</hi> Adieu, <hi>Joſeph,</hi> adieu; ſince
an all-particular Providence conducts you.
You cannot fail in your obedience, although
you may much ſuffer: Oh if your good fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
knew how many tears this Voiage will coſt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119982:32"/>
him; if he knew how many evils hang over
your head; if he knew that you are that Lamb
which you ſpake unto him of; if he knew that
your brothers were the Wolves, which would
tear you, without doubt he would not expoſe
thus your life to their fury.</p>
            <p>Let us accompany our Pilgrim, and if it be
poſſible, let us not go from him. Sometimes
he turned himſelf towards his fathers houſe:
To ſee his countenance, one would judge that
he left it with regret, and that not able to goe
there, he ſent there his ſighs. He approached
notwithſtanding to <hi>Sichem,</hi> and at the ſame
time to his death, and misfortunes. He with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew
himſelf from his father, and with the
ſame pace from his contentments. One might
judge that he ſaw all this: but he choſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
to be miſerable then diſobedient. At laſt
he arrived at a field where he thought to meet
his brethren: but finding them not, he took
a way which led him into ſo fearful a ſolitude,
that any one, as well as a young man of ſixteen
years, would have been affrighted; a leaf
trembled not without making him tremble;
every precipice was unto him a ſepulchre. Fear
perſwaded him eaſily, that the rocks raiſed not
themſelves, but to fall upon his head, and that
the deeps opened not themſelves but to bury
him. Theſe apprehenſions will laſt as long as
the Foreſt. As he engag'd himſelf in another
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119982:33"/>
Labyrinth, &amp; wandred in a ſtubble field, he met
with a man who demanded him, where goe's
<hi>Joſeph?</hi> The aſtoniſhment to hear himſelf
named by an unknown perſon, made him a
little penſive; notwithſtanding he replyed, that
he ſought his brothers, where any one (that
would do him the favour) ſhould ſhew him
them. I cannot (anſwered the ſtranger) ſhew
you preciſely the place where they are; yet
I have heard them ſay, that they would goe
unto <hi>Dothan.</hi> After this anſwer, he took leave,
when this unknown ſaid unto him, deſire you
nothing ſhould be made known to your father
<hi>Jacob?</hi> I hope to ſee him again very ſpeedily,
replyed <hi>Joſeph;</hi> that cannot be (anſwered the
ſtranger) as he was careleſſe on his way, <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi>
continued his, making reflection on the
ſalutation, and laſt words of this man. The
curioſity to ſee him again, made him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn;
but though he looked all about very care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully,
he ſaw no body, which gave him many
divers conjectures, not able to diſcern the true
from thoſe that were not ſo. In this perplexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
he perceived the Troop of his brothers,
who repoſed at the mouth of a Wood. As he
was near enough to be heard of them, he ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
them with all the civility poſſible; <hi>Sime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
who was the moſt cruel of his perſecutors,
rendred him no other complement but this:
Behold our trifler, behold that fair dreamer;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119982:33"/>
well, let us revenge us at this inſtant of all the
injuries that he hath done us, to teach him how
ſo many ſottiſh and ridiculous imaginations
have profited him. Fear not to ſtain your
hands in his blood; this action cannot be an
homicide, ſince it will be the juſt vengeance
of ſo many crimes. His words having gained
his brothers, he advanced towards <hi>Joſeph,</hi> he
ſeiſed him by the hair, and giving him kicks
with his feet, he prepared himſelf to give him
death. Our innocent Victime trembled un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
the knife, and ſeeing that he could not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure
his body, he recommended his ſoul unto
God. His eyes were glued unto Heaven, his
hands joyned, and his heart ſo full of reſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
that it appeared on his viſage, and in
his diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>My brothers, (ſaid he) I refuſe not to die,
ſince you will have it ſo; I pray you onely to
pardon me that which renders me unworthy of
your mercies. It is true, that if the ſole in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention
can offend, I am not culpable, mine
having always been innocent. But that the
ſincerity of my intentions may not be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
I will be unworthy of your affection,
ſince my actions have diſpleaſed you. It is
better to confeſſe a crime, then to blame you
of injuſtice: I condemn my ſelf, provided
that that juſtifie you. Strike, my brother,
ſtrike; notwithſtanding I conjure you, if I
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119982:34"/>
am criminal, that your pardon, and my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance
may make me die innocent. Oh how
a man, to whom cruelty and maſſacre are paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
into a nature, hath trouble to receive the
ſenſe of pity! <hi>Simeon</hi> who had done his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentiſhip
in <hi>Sichem,</hi> lifted up already his arm
to plunge death into the boſome of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> when
<hi>Reuben</hi> ſtopping the blow, cryed out, I muſt
not live to ſee <hi>Ioſeph</hi> murthered, ſo evil an acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
ſhall never have my conſent: I would that
wherein he hath offended us, his youth ſhould
excuſe him, and his tears perſwade us.</p>
            <p>Whileſt he ſaid this, <hi>Ioſeph</hi> had opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
to diſ-engage himſelf of <hi>Simeon,</hi> and to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace
the knees of <hi>Iudah,</hi> whoſe heart capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
enough of pity, grew tender at theſe
words. My brother, have compaſſion of the
poor <hi>Iacob.</hi> Theſe four or five words were
worth him no leſſe then his life, foraſmuch as
<hi>Iudah</hi> was in conſideration amongſt his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
whoſe wills were already divided upon
the deſign of this murder. Nature had not
only given him a ſupple and agile body, ſhe had
alſo choſen him an excellent ſoul; and to the
end that her benefits ſhould be entire, his tongue
was capable to expreſſe neatly the thoughts of
his ſpirit. It was therewith that he ſerv'd
himſelf to change wholly his brethren, and to
make them to be Wolves no longer: behold
his Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:119982:34"/>
How now (ſaid he) ſhall it be ſaid that the
Nephews of <hi>Abraham</hi> ſhould be Parricides, and
that the indiſcretion of a child ſhould make us
the murtherers of a brother? A word ill ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,
an extravagant dream, ſhould it give us
a reſolution ſo enraged, and a will ſo criminal
as to ſtain our hands in humane blood? I will
not excuſe <hi>Joſeph,</hi> for fear to make your deſign
appear unjuſt: but ſuppoſe that he had an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention
to procure us evil as truly as we have
received it; Tell me, if it were an <hi>Arabian</hi>
that had offended us, could we do more then
take away his life? If a wild beaſt had torn
us, ſhould we not be revenged in cutting his
throat? This here is not an <hi>Arabian,</hi> his
ſweetneſſe witneſſeth that he hath other quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties;
It is not a ſavage beaſt, nature hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
him thoſe ſenſes, which have nothing of
ſavage in them. It is one of our brothers, and
though his actions have rendred him unworthy
of that name, our goodneſſe ſhould make him
capable of our favours. And then can we put
him to death without ſhedding our proper
blood, and ſtrike him without receiving his
blowes? If he be malicious, are we obliged
to reſemble him? Certainly I underſtand not
that his example ſhould ſerve us for law, and
though he had done us outrage, the pardon of
an injury is glorious, when the revenge thereof
is eaſie. But he hath forgotten that which he
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119982:35"/>
was; let us think of that which we ought to
be. He hath conſpired againſt our life; let us
puniſh him in conſerving his: He hath taken
our honour from us, with moſt unjuſt calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies;
let us leave him live to amend. Laſtly,
though we ſhould take from him that which he
can keep no longer but by our clemency, the
world not knowing the equity of this action,
will condemn the deſign thereof. And who
can give it a good ſenſe, having no obligation
to preſume of our innocence? <hi>Jacob,</hi> I am
ſure that it ſhall not be you, yea, I am aſſured
that you will not approve an action wherein
you are outraged. Me thinks I ſee this poor
old man oppreſſed under the reſentment of this
ſorrowful news; me thinks I hear his ſighs and
ſobs, with which he accuſes his miſery. Hath
he not griefs enough, without we furniſh him
ſome in ſo lamentable a ſubject? I conjure
you, let us have pity of his evils; and if we
are loth to ſave <hi>Ioſephs</hi> life for the love of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,
let us give it him to conſerve that of our
father. Let no man ſay, that a conceal'd crime
is not much leſſe then a known innocence, and
that he that ſinneth not before men, cannot be
judged thereof. Every one of us hath a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
witneſſes, if he hath a conſcience; the
ſtings which follow a crime, do ſhew that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
can be done without being diſcovered.
But ſuppoſe that the Fields and Foreſts have
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:119982:35"/>
neither ears nor eyes to eſpy our actions: Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
that our conſciences could not produce
any teſtimony againſt us. If he who is called
the God of vengeance, and who will puniſh
every ſin with his hands, ſhould demand ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt
of this, what could we anſwer? It is
he that pierceth the deeps; it is he that ſees
the moſt ſecret thoughts: there is not darkneſs
enough to cover an action from him, nor cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
to diſguiſe the malice thereof unto him.
His eye diſcovers what is done above the Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament,
obſerves all the actions of men upon
the Earth; and though the night vails them
ſometimes, ſhe never buries them. Though
we ſhould go to offend him unto the Centre of
the Earth, we ſhould find there his Juſtice.
And though this death were equitable in being
your ſelves the Judges, he will have ſo juſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
to puniſh you, as you will have none either
to complain, or to blame him. Let us refer
the right to revenge us into the hands of him
who forbids it, and let us not ſtain ours in the
blood of our brother. This clemency will
deliver us from the reproaches of our own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,
<hi>Ioſeph</hi> from death, and our good fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
from a long train of miſeries, which
would make him either to die ſoon, or live
long time in languiſhment.</p>
            <p>Behold our little Innocent delivered from
the hands of <hi>Simeon;</hi> but ſee an accident, which
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119982:36"/>
put his life into new dangers. <hi>Levi</hi> great fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
of all the Prieſts of the Law, willing,
perhaps, to begin his ſacrifices by an accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
Victime, remonſtrates that it was a perilous
deſign to give life to an enemy, whoſe death
one had balanced: That <hi>Ioſeph</hi> not believing
himſelf guilty, would never hold himſelf ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged;
and that it was imprudence to have
made him know a will, which for his part
could not have any effect, but an irreconcilea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
hatred. As theſe reaſons began to ſhake
thoſe who inclined to ſweetneſſe, <hi>Reuben</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced
a means to ſave him, though in appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
it ſeemed that it would deſtroy him. The
death of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> is moſt juſt, (ſaid he) but I
finde the faſhion ſhameful: I cannot conſent
that we ſhould be his executioners, let us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
us to be his Judges. There is a Cyſtern
in this ſolitude, let us caſt him in there; it is
better to famiſh him, then to foul our hands
with ſo ill blood as his. This reſolution was
approved, without conſidering if it was judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious.
The ſtrongeſt but not the ſoundeſt
party carried it: They drew this poor Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent
into the deſert, they took from him that
Coat, which had been the chief cauſe of his
misfortune, they tumbled him into the Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern.
Each retired himſelf to his affairs, <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi>
remain'd plunged in the dirt of that infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
retrait, and in the ſadneſſe of that cruel
misfortune.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:119982:36"/>
Well, my God, even hitherto thou haſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered
malice to reign: <hi>Ioſeph</hi> hath been cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable,
becauſe no body hath defended his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence;
is it not time to make the Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
of thy Thunders appear upon thoſe offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
heads, who have meditated this outrage,
and the ſweetneſſe of thy Providence upon
him that merits it? Thou haſt intereſt in his
juſtification, ſince thou art the Protector of the
afflicted; if he had not been devout, he ſhould
not be miſerable. At leaſt the pretence to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe
him had been wanting to his Tyrants, if
he had not had piety. Perhaps this unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
young man hath not yet taſted bitterneſſe
enough. Oh my God, if it pleaſe thee, caſt
thy eyes upon him, I doubt not but thy heart
which is nothing but love, but thy love which
is nothing but tenderneſſe, will be touched
with the ſenſe of his miſery, and with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
to eaſe him of it.</p>
            <p>Truly it is much for an humane ſpirit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent
reaſons unto God, to perſwade him:
Do we not know yet that he pleaſeth himſelf
in the ſufferings of thoſe, who receive them
chearfully? and that their plaints are his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentments?
<hi>Ioſeph</hi> had already ſuffered much;
the envy of his brothers had furniſhed him
with malice enough to exerciſe the fair vertue
of the afflicted. The ill words which they
gave him, their calumny and their cruelty, were
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119982:37"/>
aſſaults rude enough to make him ſigh. It was
that which he did continually in his fathers
houſe; it was that which he renued in the Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern
with ſuch pitiful accents that he muſt have
had an heart more hard then marble that
would not bee touched therewith: behold
ſome of his plaints.</p>
            <p>Alas! muſt I for being obedient be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
miſerable? and for witneſſing my reſpect
incurre thy indignation? My God, thou
knoweſt that I was never guilty of the ſins of
which they accuſe me, and that if I have offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
any one, it hath been either through ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance
or ſimplicity. It is true, that my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
ſometimes expreſſed more affection to me
then to my brothers; but muſt his goodneſſe
make me ſuſpected of malice, and the Careſſes
which he gave not but to my Infancy, make
more then the moity of my crimes? I do not
ſay this to accuſe thy goodneſſe, which cannot
fail, nor to juſtifie my innocence, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
be perfect, if thou uſe all thy rigour.
Though my vertue ſhould be without ſpot, thy
only will would render my affliction lawful, and
the fault of my enemies pardonable. I die
willingly in this priſon, and will no longer
draw a languiſhing life, which is not pleaſing
to thee. Let hunger conſume me, let the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents
tear me, it ſhall make nothing againſt my
deſire, ſince nothing arrives againſt thy Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119982:37"/>
Onely (my God) I conjure thee to
forget my faults, and to have pity of the ſoul
of that poor culpable wretch, who dyes, either
to ſatisfie thy juſtice, or to obey thy holy and
adorable will.</p>
            <p>Whileſt <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſighed, our Paſtours who
were gone to gather together their Flocks and
Herd, came all to the place where the rendez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouz
was appointed. <hi>Reuben</hi> only was want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;
for he ſtepped aſide into the wood to be able
ſafely to draw his brother out of the Ceſtern:
His abſence was not ſuſpected of that good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention,
having himſelf given the counſel to
caſt him in there. As he thought on the means
of this deliverance, his brothers, who were on
the High-way, perceived afar off a Troop of
<hi>Iſmaelites,</hi> who ſeemed to advance towards
them. As ſoon as <hi>Judas</hi> underſtood that they
were Merchants, it came into his thought to
prolong <hi>Joſephs</hi> life, ſince that he had not pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
to warrant him from death. My brethren,
(ſaid he) the Image of that miſerable creature
appears alwayes before mine eyes; I believe if
he dye in the eſtate wherein we leave him, that
the remembrance of his death will be hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward
a ſad phantaſme that will trouble me
night and day. Behold, a fair occaſion not
only to puniſh, but alſo to profit by his malice.
Let us ſell him to theſe <hi>Iſmaelites,</hi> our revenge
ſhall be more ſafe, ſince they withdraw them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119982:38"/>
ordinarily towards <hi>Egypt.</hi> This propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition
pleaſed, and was generally received of
all the others, <hi>Judas</hi> accompanied with ſome of
them ran to the Ceſtern. In the moment that he
arrived, our innocent <hi>Joſeph</hi> entertain'd himſelf
upon the thoughts of the amorous Providence
of God; as he ſaw in the bottom of the cave ſom
one, that ſeemed to approach unto him, he eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
believed that it was death; he knew notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
that it was the ſhadow of <hi>Judas,</hi> who
commanded him to hold faſt by a cord to be
the more eaſily drawn forth. He obeyed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
this belief, that they could not finde a cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eller
death, then that which was ſure unto him
in this pit. They led him on the way where
the <hi>Iſmaelites</hi> were arrived, and treated already
of this purchaſe. Having ſeen how he beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
himſelf, his graceful carriage, and his beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
gained ſo ſenſibly their hearts, that a load
of gold would not have diſpleaſed them for
this Merchandiſe; but thoſe who knew not
the merit of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> cared not to ſet on him ſo
high a price. They left him for thirty pence,
as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> aſſureth it; may be to the end
that this figure ſhould accord to the truth, and
the ſhadow repreſent perfectly its Sun. The
Merchants could apprehend that this young
man was not robbed, ſince they gave him ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
then ſold him. Notwithſtanding the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit
being to their profit, they counted readily
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:119982:38"/>
that which they had deſired of them. One of
them obſerving their mirth, not to appear ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
ſots, or deceivers, ſaid unto them, Sirs,
It is ſimplicity to deceive ones ſelf, malice to
deceive others. The bone-mine of this young
man might make us to be thought fools for
ſelling him ſo cheap. To the end that you
have not this opinion of us, nor take a worſe,
I would fain advertiſe you of his qualities.
Know that you never ſaw one more gentle, but
take heed that the Magick, in which he excels,
do not take him out of your hands. This ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe
made them not repent to have hazarded
the little which he coſt them; notwithſtanding
the belief that he was a Magician, gave them a
little more care then they would have taken of
him otherwiſe. The poor <hi>Joſeph</hi> fearing that
there could not arrive unto him a greater miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief,
eſteemed that of ſlavery ſweet enough,
diſſembling by the ſerenity of his countenance,
the ſadneſſe of his heart.</p>
            <p>Let us leave him with his Maſters, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn
we to <hi>Reuben,</hi> who perhaps loſt himſelf in
the ſolitude where we left him. The Evening
of this Journy began to approach, and the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows
as it were to prepare the Earth for the
darkneſs of the night extended themſelves deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
into the field, when the beſt of all the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
of <hi>Joſeph</hi> came to the Ceſtern. He lean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
on its banks, looking of all ſides, if he
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:119982:39"/>
could ſee him whom he ſought; but having
perceived nothing, he called <hi>Joſeph:</hi> belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
that he was deceived, he fixed his ſight
more curiouſly upon all the places of this Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern;
and ſeeing no more there then at firſt, he
redoubled his voice, but <hi>Ioſeph</hi> anſwer'd not.
It was then that <hi>Reuben</hi> imagined the Serpents,
and Vipers which were in great number there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about,
had deſtroyed him. It would be hard
to deſcribe the plaints which he made upon
this belief, accuſing ſometimes the perfidiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
of his brothers, and now his own wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe.
A thouſand ſighs iſſued from his
mouth, and as many tears from his eyes: if he
ſhould have remained long by this Ceſtern,
there had needed no other rain to fill it but
that of his eyes. But (ſaid he) thy regrets can
prevail nothing upon death; ſhe is as deaf as
blinde: Let us not loſe words unprofitably,
and ſince that my ſins have cauſed this loſſe, let
us ſhew more patience to ſuffer it, then we have
expreſs'd courage to hinder it. As he had fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed
this word he put himſelf in indevour to
ſeek his brothers, whom he found driving their
Herds towards the Village: As far off as they
could hear him, he cryed out, we have no bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
more, <hi>Ioſeph</hi> is dead. Theſe three words
made all the company ſtop, who ſeeing on
<hi>Reubons</hi> countenance the marks of his grief,
took from him the errour wherein he was, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119982:39"/>
that neceſſity had conſtrained them to
make this traffick. To ingage him in their
fault, they gave him three of thoſe ſilver pieces,
with which they had been paid. All the night
was paſſed in conſulting on the means to cover
their crime. The beſt expedient on which
they adviſed themſelves, was to kill a Kid,
and to dip <hi>Ioſephs</hi> coat in his blood, to the end
to make <hi>Iacob</hi> believe, that ſome wild beaſt
had devoured him in the deſert, proteſting with
horrible Oaths, that he who ſhould ſay other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe,
ſhould not be recompenſed for that piety
but with death.</p>
            <p>I aſſure me, my dear Reader, that you will
have much trouble to ſee the poor <hi>Iacob</hi> in this
encounter without tears, whether they be yours
or his; he was ſate before his door with the
little <hi>Benjamin;</hi> when his children ſaw him,
each of them compoſed himſelf ſo perfectly
unto ſadneſs, that one would have believed
that they reſented the true effects thereof. <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meon</hi>
who was to make this evil diſcourſe, had
not only diſguiſed his viſage, but his artifice
was paſſed even unto the heart, to draw thence
the ſighs of the Crocodile: He had alſo medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated
the ſimpleſt words that he could chuſe,
to the end to make no ſtudy nor policy appear
in his ſpeech. Being then come to this good
Patriarch, he cried out with an accent very pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful:
Oh my Father, we have no more bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119982:40"/>
               <hi>Ioſeph</hi> is dead; and then drawing forth
the Coat which he carried, behold all that
which a cruel beaſt hath left us of him. Know
you not the fair robe of the moſt amiable of
your children? This was here the laſt word of
his diſcourſe, foraſmuch as he had prepared ſo
many ſighs and tears, that the reſt thereof ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
to be ſmothered under their abundance.
To repreſent perfectly the firſt effect which this
news wrought upon <hi>Jacob,</hi> it is neceſſary to
lay a ſtatue of marble before your eyes. The
blow being not expected, it did like a Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derbolt
whoſe clap ſuſpends all our powers,
until we have made reflection upon our own
danger. This Image is lively enough for that
firſt aſſault of grief, but we muſt have other
ſhapes to repreſent him, when he had a little
look'd upon the ſubject of his affliction. This
poor old man taking the lamentable reliques
of his ſon, cryed out, <hi>Ioſeph</hi> is dead, my ſon
<hi>Ioſeph</hi> is no more, and then conſidering the
ſpots of blood in the Coat: Oh cruel mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,
I may well ſay, ſince ſo much ſweetneſſe
could not perſwade thee that cruelty it ſelf is
thy proper nature. Perhaps I dream, and this
is not the robe of my ſon, yet it hath the work
thereof: It is the ſame, and where are you
then <hi>Ioſeph?</hi> Oh my dear <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> you are
dead. But if you are no more, ſhould I live,
my life being not but yours? I perceive by
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119982:40"/>
this rent of the ſide, that the wild beaſt hath
planted his murtherous teeth in your innocent
heart. Muſt thou then inhumane monſter, muſt
thou attach the ſource of all my loves: Alas,
<hi>Ioſeph</hi> is no more.</p>
            <p>Behold all that which our afflicted Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch
ſaid, making appear that his grief was
true, ſeeing it was not eloquent, and that he
ſuffered many evils, ſince he expreſs'd them
but very little. All the inhabitants of <hi>Hebron</hi>
who indevoured to comfort him, had no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
anſwer but this, <hi>Ioſeph</hi> is dead, will you
have me live? no, no; keep your reaſons for
ſome other, who hath leſſe cauſe to lament
then I. I will that my tears accompany me
even to my Tomb, and if the dead could car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
their paſſions thither, I would that the grief
my be immortal, and that it might make the
moity of my ſoul. Adieu pleaſures, adieu
<hi>Ioſeph,</hi> adieu only <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> ſince I bid adieu to
all that which is ſweet and amiable in this
life, in bidding you adieu. This was the
only complement with which he received his
comforters; ſoon after, as if he were returned
from a long trance, he added: But it may be
that my ſon hath quitted his robe, and that
this beaſt hath found it. Sottiſh reaſon! thou
indeavoureſt to deceive mee; and whence
comes this blood? and why this rage againſt
an inanimate thing? You would have belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:119982:41"/>
ſeeing theſe good, and his evil intervals,
that nature reſtrained of grief, took breath, to
the end to be more ſenſible of it afterward. So
it was that <hi>Zabulon</hi> not able to behold longer
the diſpleaſure of his father, took a reſolution
to diſcover the ſecret to him, if the fear which
his brothers gave him of a cruel death, had
not ſhut his mouth. This ſilence was not a
vertue, ſince to the treaſon againſt <hi>Ioſeph</hi> it ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
the hazard to make <hi>Iacob</hi> dye. But ſince
that our diſcourſe can neither wipe away, nor
deſcribe the tears of this deſolate father, let us
permit him that which the moſt cruel Tyrants
forbid not to the afflicted, and let us follow
his miſerable ſon into <hi>Egypt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the <hi>Iſhmaelites</hi> were arrived to the
Fountain of <hi>Shilo,</hi> which is near unto <hi>Bethle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hem,</hi>
our ſlave perceived a Pyramid erected up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
a Tomb, which he knew to be that of his
mother. The deſire to give a laſt kiſſe to the
marble, which covered her holy reliques, made
him take his courſe towards that place. The
Merchants who ſaw him ſtretched out upon
that Tomb, had ſome ſuſpition that he was a
Necromancer, and that he ſpake to the dead,
according to the belief that was given them
of his Magick. Whileſt they entertained
themſelves in this thought, <hi>Ioſeph</hi> indeavour'd
to diſcover his unto <hi>Rahel.</hi> Alas, my good
mother (ſaid he) if you keep yet that pitiful
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119982:41"/>
and loving heart, which you had formerly,
will you not make it appear unto me at this
preſent that I am loaden with theſe chains,
with the moſt ſenſible miſery, that could aſſault
a ſtrong patience? I am aſſured that your ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
gives you a great power with the God of
<hi>Abraham;</hi> could you better imploy it then to
the relief of Innocents? I deſire not that my
merit be the motive of your benefit, becauſe
that being ſo little, I cannot expect from it ſo
notable a ſuccour: It ſhall be if it pleaſe you,
your goodneſſe, which never found any thing
difficult, provided, that it was reaſonable. I
deſire not that God would puniſh the ſins of my
brethren, I love better their repentance then
their death: I wiſh not that my life be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed,
a ſweet death ſeems more deſirable un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
me then a languiſhing life. Behold then the
ſubject of all my devotions: Grant, my ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
mother, that this ſtone, open it ſelf, and
permit me to dye in the ſame boſome, where I
began to live. This favour is great, if you
meaſure it according to the eſteem that I make
thereof: But then it is he whoſe birth wip'd
away the tears of ſeven years, that demands it;
it is he to whom you wiſhed ſo many bleſſings,
whereas you ſee me charged with ſo many miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes;
It is in a word your ſon <hi>Ioſeph:</hi>
can you refuſe him this favour at leſſe rate then
to be no more mother?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:119982:42"/>
As he pronounced theſe words, his eyes ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed
the Tomb, and his ſighs made his maſters
underſtand ſufficiently that he had more affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
in his heart, then deſign of Magick in his
action. Having drawn him notwithſtanding
from this Sepulchre, where it ſeemed that love
had tyed him, they continued their way to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<hi>Egypt;</hi> but it was not without thinking
of his actions, and without weighing all the
words of our Captive. Above all ſome obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
with much aſtoniſhment, that this young
man gathered up certain little ſtones by that
Tomb. The moſt judicious of theſe ſtrangers
ſeeing I know not what of extraordinary upon
the viſage, and in the diſcourſe of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved
aſſuredly, that though he had the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
of a ſlave, he had not the birth of one.
This thought gave him the curioſity to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
of him, why he fixed himſelf upon that
Tomb, and who he was. The young man taking
the liberty w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> they gave him to ſpeak, replyed.</p>
            <p>Sir, If I went away from you as ſoon as I
perceived that Pyramid, I did it not upon any
apprehenſion not to obtain that favour from
your courteſie, but the remembrance of my
dear mother preventing all my other thoughts,
took from me that of my duty, and carryed me
farther towards her then I had permiſſion for.
Know then, that my Father paſſing ſome ten
years ſince by <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> which you ſee, my
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119982:42"/>
mother was ſurpriſed in this Land with the
throwes of child-bearing, of which a few
days after ſhe dyed. My Father who had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
loved her, as ſhe deſerved, would yet wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
it after her death, erecting her this Pyra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mid,
where he graved the name of his dear
wife, and that of all his childreu. The young
man ended his diſcourſe, when his maſter
commanded him to tell the place of his birth,
his name, and that of his parents: he did it
with ſo good grace, that it was ſufficient to
win the heart of an <hi>Arabian,</hi> and to deſerve to
be freed of the chains with which he was loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den.</p>
            <p>One might here demand why theſe <hi>Iſmaelites</hi>
took no reſolution to bring him back to his
Father. The queſtion is not ſo eaſie, as it
ſeems at firſt. For to ſay that they believed
not the diſcourſe, which he had made them,
the good uſage which he received from them,
ſhewed wel that they held him not for an Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtour.
Was it that they knew not <hi>Iacob?</hi> This
reaſon cannot be good, ſince he was nephew
to <hi>Iſmael</hi> their Grandfather. Perhaps they
apprehended the vengeance of thoſe who had
ſold him; what probability for that, ſince
their force was equall unto theirs? Shall we
believe that the fair parts of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> might make
them hope a great profit by his ſale? I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe
that intereſt can much upon a merce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119982:43"/>
ſoul, but from whom could they hope
more then from a father, who loved perfectly;
then from a father who knew well the merit
of ſuch a ſon; then from a father, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
lived no more, in that he ſuppoſed <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi>
was dead. Though we ſhould have
brought all the conjectures, we ſhould not have
touched the true reaſon. I love better to reject
the ſmall appearances of my reaſoning, and have
recourſe to that Providence which governed
all the fortunes of our <hi>Ioſeph;</hi> Providence
which ſometimes takes pleaſure to blind all the
wiſdome of men, to the end to conduct her
deſigns, by ways as amorous as they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known.
How many times have we ſeen the
wiſe men of the world, and thoſe wits which
we flatter with ſtrength and intelligence, to
looſe diſcourſe in the events, whereas infancy
could ſpeak Learnedly? God pleaſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
ſometimes to make us confeſſe, that wee
have no light, but what he thinks fit to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate
unto us. We need not wonder then
if theſe <hi>Iſhmaelites</hi> ſaw not the advantages w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi>
the deliverance of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> would bring them,
ſince God concealed them to make his deſigns
ſucceed. Whileſt we divert us thus pleaſingly,
<hi>Ioſeph</hi> changes Country, and becomes a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.
Some have written that he was ſold
twice before he entred into <hi>Egypt.</hi> That which
hath made them to erre, was that they were
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:119982:43"/>
ignorant that the names of <hi>Iſhmaelites,</hi> of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabians,</hi>
and of <hi>Madianites,</hi> were not but one
and the ſame people. Howſoever it was, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
engaging me in theſe difficulties, willing
to unfold them, it is certain that our Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants
ſteer'd right to the Royal Town, where
they believed that fortune would ſooner at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
them then any where elſe. Being arriv'd
there, their firſt care was not to admire the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perb
buildings of that famous City: Every one
hath his thoughts, and his divertiſements,
thoſe of the Merchants are to procure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
riches. The occupation of ours was to
expoſe preſently their merchandiſes, and
though the Maſter was troubled to reſolve
himſelf that <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſhould be the richeſt piece
thereof: Notwithſtanding the deſire of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney
carried him for this bout, above the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration
of his pleaſures. It is true that he
put ſo great a price upon him, as could buy a
ſcore of other ſlaves, and which would have
driven away all the world, if his merit had
not been as viſible as his graceful behaviour.
One day theſe <hi>Iſhmaelites</hi> being upon the point
to depart, a Lady of condition paſſed by their
ſhop: As ſhe perceived our ſlave, ſhe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
her Coach to ſtop, and having conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered
him, an Eunuch told the Merchants that
they ſhould not depart the Town till they had
received my Ladies Orders. It was not hard
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119982:44"/>
to obey a Lady of that quality; So the ſtay was
not long, for <hi>Potiphar</hi> ſent them at the howre
a Page to command them to come to his houſe,
and to bring with them that young <hi>Cananean,</hi>
whom his wife had entertained. The Kite flies
not more ſwiftly to his prey, then theſe men of
money rendred themſelves where they hoped to
find theirs. They ſpake without delay of the
price, which appeared not exceſſive, becauſe
they had no ſooner ſeen <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> but they bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
the <hi>Iſhmaelites</hi> for not making the eſteem
of him which they ought. His countenance
ſhewed well that he was not of the Village, and
his liberty which he had free amongſt his Irons.
<hi>Potiphar</hi> asked him, what he could do? To
which he anſwered with an incredible mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty,
that he could obey; this reply was ſo
much more pleaſing, as it was leſſe expected.
This Lord who took pleaſure to hear him,
would engage him to other anſwers. What
then, cannot one command thee any thing ſo
hard that is not impoſſible for thee? My
Lord, replyed <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> obedience conſiſts not
in doing, but in willing, ſo that if one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands
any thing above our power, our weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
is rather ſeen then our vice. If I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
thee to adore our Gods, added <hi>Poti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phar?</hi>
That would be impoſſible for me, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed
our ſlave, ſince you have not any. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
that they be not ſo as thou wilt, I can or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:119982:44"/>
thee to render the ſame honours that we
do to the Crocodiles. Then I would not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey,
becauſe my obedience would be a crime,
by reaſon of a duty more preſſing then the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation
that I ſhould have to accompliſh your
will. Whileſt <hi>Ioſeph</hi> gave theſe couragious
anſwers, <hi>Potiphar</hi> fixing too curiouſly his eyes
upon a face of ſeventeen years, took a paſſion
for this ſlave, which is too filthy to be named,
and without diminiſhing any thing of the price,
told forth an hundred Crowns of gold to his
Maſters. God ſtayed not long to puniſh the
raſhneſſe of a man that would profane a thing
which was conſecrate to him. S. <hi>Ierome</hi> aſſures
that concupiſcence was ſo quenched in this
Lord, that not only he could not ſeek the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden
pleaſures, but alſo he was not capable
of the lawful. Perhaps the Scripture hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
occaſion from thence to call him Eunuch,
which could not be before, ſince he had a
daughter ten years old.</p>
            <p>This accident cooled the body of <hi>Potiphar,</hi>
not his affection: On the contrary it increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
inſomuch that he took a perfect knowledge
of his good qualities. Vertue makes it ſelf al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
to be cheriſhed; ſo muſt it be granted
that being more fair in a fair body, ſhe hath
charms more powerful, and attractions leſſe
avoidable; <hi>Ioſephs</hi> Maſter learn'd this truth
from his experience; for having continually
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:119982:45"/>
this young man before his eyes, and not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
of his perfections, by little and little he
formed himſelf a neceſſity to love him, and
from that love a moſt perfect confidence. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
the good qualities with which he ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
himſelf commendable, he had one that
ſeemed not to be of his age: It was a pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
ſo ordered, that one would think it old
from an age. It was ſhe that rendred him hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py
in <hi>Potiphars</hi> houſe, inaſmuch as he truſted
him with all the government of his houſe, and
with the intendency of all his affairs. This
confidence was not dammageable, ſince <hi>Ioſeph</hi>
was an Intelligence that could neither be ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed
in his conduct, nor corrupted in his
manners. Never ſuffered he himſelf to be van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed
with the deſire of wealth, nor wearied
himſelf to practiſe it. The hand of an Angel
was not more clean of avarice then his; and
though gold hath I know not what of glutto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous,
he could not be catched therewith. He
made the riches of his Maſter to profit, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
diminiſhing thoſe of his neighbours. His
debtors could ſay, that it was advantageous to
them to have ſuch a Creditour. To ſee the
wealth of <hi>Potiphar,</hi> one would have ſaid, that
all the ſuperfluity of <hi>Egypt</hi> flowed into his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace,
and that this fair part of the world was
not fruitful but for him. Judge now if this
ſervant was uſed like a ſlave; and if his Maſter
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:119982:45"/>
had reproaches for him. The other Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks
drew not the ſame ſatisfaction from <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,</hi>
foraſmuch as his cares were a continual
cenſure of their negligence. Sometimes they
had temerity enough to blame a vertue which
they could not imitate; but <hi>Potiphar</hi> was not
diſpoſed to their murmures, and the integrity
of his oeconomy made their envy appear. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
the aſſurance which he had there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
never made him inſolent: On the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
perſwading himſelf that he ought as well to
conſerve the peace of that houſe as his own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts,
he prevented the other Officers with all
ſort of good offices. If he preſented himſelf
any benefit, it fell by his addreſſe into other
hands then his; making more reckoning of a
friend, then of a preſent. Never demanded
<hi>Potiphar</hi> of him an account of his companions
deportments, that he had not good to ſay of
them. This induſtry gained him by little
and little the moſt ſavage, and the moſt jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous.</p>
            <p>A man that treats thus with his inferiours,
fails not ordinarily of the reſpect that he owes
to his Lord: <hi>Ioſeph</hi> might ſay that he was
rather adored, then that he received honour
thereby. His fortune might make him believe
that he was his Favorite, notwithſtanding he
never thought himſelf but his ſlave. The af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection
which they bare him augmented his
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:119982:46"/>
reverence, in ſtead of leſſening it.</p>
            <p>I have ſaid that <hi>Potiphar</hi> had a daughter, but
I have not yet ſaid that ſhe was ſo born unto
good, and that all her inclinations were ſo
innocent, that <hi>Ioſeph</hi> not able to hate verue,
cheriſhed the viſage thereof in his young Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe.
The effects of this love were all chaſt
and all holy, as well as their cauſe. As this
Gentlewoman began to grow up, ſhe began
to be conſidered as the faireſt and richeſt
match of <hi>Egypt.</hi> Her houſe was ordinarily
filled with young Lords, who came to make
themſelves ſlaves unto her, who would have
no ſervants. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> having known this incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,
and obſerved that the heart of <hi>Aſſeneth</hi>
rejected all that which her eyes attracted, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devoured
to fortifie her in that reſolution. When
he met her aſide, and that he could not be
heard of her Followers, he told her ſo many
marvels of chaſtity, that ſhe deliberated
from that time forward to remain always
a Virgin. Obſerve this paſſage of Gods
Providence, who diſtaſted this Maid with the
love of all thoſe that ſought her, to prepare
her to an affection which you will preſently
admire.</p>
            <p>But it ſeems that fortune was weary to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige
our Intendant, and that ſhe feared to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
the name of conſtant, if ſhe obliged him
longer. And to ſpeak truth, I ſhould love
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:119982:46"/>
much better to be alwayes miſerable, then not
to be happy, but to reſent more livelily my
misfortune, and to creep in the duſt, then to
ſee my ſelf lifted up to fall into a preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pice.
There is no beaſt how fierce ſoever he
be, who becomes not gentle with us: Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes
ſeem to be of this nature, ſince the
moſt bitter render themſelves ſweet by their
familiarity. Poor <hi>Joſeph</hi> how happy had you
been in your misfortune, if they had left you
to the chain; the cuſtome of ſuffering would
have taken away the ſenſe of your pains, or at
leaſt it would have diminiſhed the ſharpneſſe
thereof.</p>
            <p>Hitherto we have not ſpoken of the ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
which the wife of <hi>Potiphar</hi> had from the
ſervices of <hi>Joſeph:</hi> We have ſaid that all
thoſe of the houſe lov'd him perfectly, ſhall
it be ſhe alone that hath no heart? Oh would
to God that ſhe were all of Ice for him, her
hate is more to be deſired then her affection.
They aſſure that Love hath no eyes, or if he
have, he ſees not a whit; this cannot be ſaid
of thoſe that love. For if the object of their
paſſion be preſent, it poſſeſſeth not only their
thought, but as if all their looks belonged to
it, it draws them ſo powerfully, that reaſon
governs them no more. And that which is
to be admired, they are ſo clear-ſighted,
that they find in that object the perfections
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:119982:47"/>
that are not there. Every part is a miracle
of nature, and though oftentimes that very
thing, from whence they derive their love, is
that which gives hatred unto others, it muſt
be that all their compariſons come from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
and that the names which they give them
be robbed from the Angels, or from God. But
retnrn we to her who muſt make the filthieſt
part of this Hiſtory, and which we would
have left out if the Holy Ghoſt himſelf mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
all its particulars, ſeemed not willing to
illuſtrate the glory of <hi>Joſeph</hi> by the ſhame of
this infamous woman. It is not then but too
true, that he was loved of her, who owed all
her heart to <hi>Potiphar,</hi> which ſhe could not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide
without loſing it altogether. I confeſſe
notwithſtanding that her firſt affection had
taken birth from his fair qualities, and that
ſhe was in the beginning honeſt; but degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating
afterward into a filthy paſſion, ſhe fixed
her ſelf leſſe to the merit, then to him that
poſſeſſed it. Behold as it happeneth often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times,
that Vertues ingender Vices, and that
the Sun produceth the ſhadows, which he muſt
diſſipate. <hi>Joſeph</hi> perceived not ſo ſoon the
malady of his Miſtreſſe, foraſmuch as he ſaw
nothing amiable in his perſon, and that he
had too good opinion of <hi>Cyrene,</hi> to conceive
an evil one of her. It is thus that charity thinks
of her neighbour, loving better to feign perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:119982:47"/>
in him, then to conſider his defects: ſhe
doth that here which ſhe would find All the
words of complaiſance which ſhe uſed, were
taken for a ſimple acceptation of ſervice, and
for a civility, which the Nobility never deny
to the meaneſt perſons.</p>
            <p>This woman perceiving the ſenſe that <hi>Ioſeph</hi>
gave to her flatteries, declared her ſelf all open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
not letting any occaſion paſſe to witneſſe
to him her love. She had no praiſes but for
<hi>Joſeph;</hi> all that which he did was approved,
his leaſt words were myſteries, and though ſhe
needed not to feign much to find him fair, her
paſſion rendred him to her more amiable. If
this evil had not been gone ſo far, there might
have been means to cure it, and to give ſome
excuſe to a woman, who had no modeſty. For
to ſpeak the truth, one muſt be extreamly cold
not to be warmed by ſo fair a fire, and ſtrong
to make defence againſt ſo charming an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.
His beauty was a powerful attraction, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
for the ſouls that were not weak. The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity
of theſe <hi>Moors</hi> and <hi>Aethopians,</hi> who
were in the ſame houſe, ſerving him for um<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brage,
raiſed his luſtre the more. What mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel
was it then that a woman made like the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe
of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> ſhould ſuffer her ſelf to be
taken by ſo many enticements!</p>
            <p>Our holy young man knew at laſt the evil
gain that he had made; and as all was contrived
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:119982:48"/>
without his conſent, and againſt his deſire, he
indevoured to bring to it all the remedies that
his wiſdome judged neceſſary and profitable.
The preſence of the object is the ſupport and
nouriſhment of that diſeaſe, which they call
Love; he was not ignorant of it, therefore
withdrew he as much as he could from this
Lady. But if neceſſity obliged him to do any
thing in her preſence, he reſtrained all the good
grace of his action, for fear that it might be a
new motive to her tenderneſſe. His artifices
ſtaid not there; for as he knew that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained
without fruit, being angry with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
for the fault of another, he puniſhed it in
his perſon. He faſted, wore the cilice, and
practiſed other mortifications, to the end to
take away the handſomeneſſe from his body,
and the beauty from his viſage, which ſeemed
to prepare him this perſecution. He that kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles
a fire, ought to quench it; when Love is
unlawful, his birth is ſhameful, his murther
commendable: the Parricide is the true fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
thereof; for who kills it, obliges it.</p>
            <p>The more our Saint applied induſtries to
diſ-engage his Miſtreſſe, the more his Miſtreſſe
invented new plots to ſurpriſe him. All her
actions carried deſign; her looks were capable
to bring impurity into a pure ſpirit, and to
make a ſavage to love. Her countenance was
ſo ſmooth, that it could give tenderneſſe to the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:119982:48"/>
moſt auſtere vertue. Even her carriage, when it
appeared ſimple, was affected. I ſpeak not of
the ſighs, with which ſhe indevoured to ſhake
his conſtancy, nor of certain papers, which
ſhe made ſometimes to fly into his hands. I
care not to trouble your chaſte ears with the
evil diſcourſes that ſhe held forth unto him;
but to the end that you may know the ſtrength
of a great ſoul, I will give you part of his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.
The wiſe Phyſician draws Antidotes
from the moſt cruel poiſon; the good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
inſtructions from the moſt evil actions.</p>
            <p>This unchaſte Lady having one day declared
unto him the paſſion that ſhe had for him, and
indevoured to draw his conſent to her ſhameful
deſign, he ſaid unto her couragiouſly. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,
I ſhould never have thought that a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
of your quality ſhould be of your humour,
and that you could have filthy paſſions in a
condition, which obliges you to have none but
noble. To ſpeak ſeriouſly, I believe that your
proceeding is not but artifice, to underſtand if
I am as fooliſh, as I am young. I cannot ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine
that a Lady, who is as it were in all the
eyes of the world, who conſerves hitherto ſo
clean a reputation, who hath kept a perfect fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity
to her husband, and who gives one of
the faireſt examples unto <hi>Egypt,</hi> ſhould receive
the thoughts that one might condemn. Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don
me, if I complain of the experience which
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:119982:49"/>
you would make of my faith, and if I tell you
that I think not to have ſo ill husbanded the
affairs of my Lord, that I ſhould be prodigal
of his honour, which I know to be the moſt
precious of all his wealth. Grant notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
that your paſſion be as true, as you
command me to believe it, I will not fear to
tell you, that it ſhall always be more eaſie for
me to dye innocent, then to live unfaithful.
Should not my head moſt merit the Thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolt
of any mans under Heaven, to betray
a perſon, whoſe truſt obliges me to be a good
man? What water would be pure enough to
waſh me of the ſpot which ſo wicked, and cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal
an ingratitude would caſt upon my repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation?
My Maſter hath commanded that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
one obey me in his houſe, (ſhe only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted,
who muſt command me here, what ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance
is there of acknowledgement of ſo
many benefits from the moſt ſenſible outrage,
that he could expect from his moſt cruel ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my?
But though the conſideration of my
duty would not take from me the liberty of
ſo black a crime, and that your paſſion would
abandon you to the meaneſt of your ſervants, I
have higher thoughts to hinder me from being
Traitor and Adulterer both together. If the
God which I adore, were like unto yours,
who ſees not but the hay of his cratch, the
aſſurance not to be perceived, would take from
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:119982:49"/>
me the fear to be puniſhed. But alas! his eyes
pierce into the deeps, and his juſtice cannot
ſuffer the leaſt faults without puniſhment. Let
us hide us to offend him, we ſhall do the ſame
as if we ſhould ſhut our eyes, to hinder a Lynx
from ſeeing us. Let us retire into the ſolitudes
to aſſure our ſin: His hand will go along to
take us, to puniſh it. The night and darkneſs
are not more cloudy, and obſcure to him then
mid-day; nor the two ends of the world more
diſtant from his Majeſty, then the Centre of
the Sun, where he hath choſen his habitation.
What impunity can one hope in offending a
God, who knows all things, and pardoneth
nothing? Suffer me then, Madam, to live
innocent in your houſe, or if my life cannot
be pleaſing to you being vertuous, give mee
leave to ſeek one, where I may be acceptable
being faithful.</p>
            <p>If the paſſions would become ſometimes tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctable
unto reaſon, this diſcourſe was wiſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough
to correct that of <hi>Cyrene;</hi> but theſe
motions of the brutiſh part of man would
be no more the Tyrants of his ſoul, if they
ſhould obey judgement; and the ſpirit would
be abſolute, if it had no longer Rebels in it's
Empire. Expect not then change in <hi>Joſeph's</hi>
Miſtreſſe, if it be not that theſe ſparks kindle
into a coal. Love hath this evil quality, that
he ſtubbornly diſputes againſt the remedies,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:119982:50"/>
and encreaſeth like the flames by the agitation
of all that, which is contrary to it. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance
of this generous Champion was not
capable to change ſo evil a deſign, nor to heal
her, who took pleaſure to be ſick; On the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary,
his modeſty made her impudence to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe,
and his refuſal augmented her importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities.
As we ſee ſometimes the water to kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle
the fire by a ſecret vertue, to which the
Philoſopher gives a name, without knowing
its nature. Yet conſidering that her laſcivious
glances were no darts to vanquiſh the courage
of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> and that all the beauty which ſhe
borrowed from the <hi>fucus,</hi> and from art, could
not enter into that chaſt heart, nor ſlide it ſelf
into his ſoul, ſhe had recourſe to other charms
then her own, endevouring to make her ſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved
of an Angel, by the aſſiſtance of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils,
<hi>Egypt</hi> hath always been the mother of
Sorceries; and if the Hiſtory thereof may be
believed, the Devil never found a Province,
which had like diſpoſitions to his Impoſtures.
This poor miſerable of whom we ſpeak, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
added to her former deceits great number
of love-potions, and known that the vertue of
<hi>Joſeph</hi> was a counter-poiſon to all her venom,
reſolved her ſelf to have recourſe to a Sorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſe,
who boaſted to gain all hearts, upon
whom ſhe ſhould have deſign. Love, how ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream
is thy violence, ſince thy motions carry a
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:119982:50"/>
ſoul even unto Hell! How deep is thy blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
ſince thy obſcurity extinguiſhes in us the
faireſt lights of the Heaven!</p>
            <p>Behold then the wife of <hi>Potiphar,</hi> who came
into the houſe of the Witch, with one ſole
Confident, and under an unknown habit. Vice
hath ſometimes the diſcretion to cover it ſelf;
but it pretends by this modeſty to give it ſelf
more liberty, not to hinder the ſcandall, or
to puniſh its malice. As ſoon as ſhe ſaw this
Proſerpine, ſhe ſaid unto her, My good mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
you know already the cauſe that brings
me to you. The gods have not communicated
unto you all their knowledge, that you ſhould
not ſee my diſaſter: I come to her who holds
their power in her hand, and who hath as well
as they the will to ſuccour the miſerable.
Make me to reſent the effects of your pity; and
ſince you change beaſts more ſavage then that
cruel one who makes me dye, give him a moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
of the flames that conſume me, or commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate
me the Ice that congealeth him. If the
acknowledgement of it can pay a benefit, you
may be aſſured, that neither the power nor the
will ſhall be wanting to me in this occaſion.</p>
            <p>My daughter, (replyed the Sorcereſſe) I
know the cauſe of your coming, I know the
evil that torments you, and am not ignorant
of the remedy, which ſhall cure you. Have
only a firm confidence that there is nothing
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:119982:51"/>
impoſſible to the force of my charms, and I
will loſe all my credit, if you loſe not all
your inquietudes. Before three days be paſt
you ſhall triumph on your Rebel; follow me.
Having ended her promiſes, ſhe conducted her
Victime into a Cloſet filled with Skeletons of
dead born infants, with skins of Serpents, with
Images of wax, with blood, and with an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
of ſuch like moveables. After having
filled her ſpirit with illuſions, ſhe put a pouder
into her hand, which ſhe ſhould uſe in making
it alſo to be mingled in <hi>Joſephs</hi> meat. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over
ſhe gave her a little piece of Virgin-parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
marked with Characters written in
Rere-mouſe-blood, to the end to ſow it into
ſome part of his clothes. Demand not if theſe
drugs coſt dear, for nothing is chargeable to
the perſon that loves. Profuſeneſſe follows
ordinarily Love, and poverty follows that this
traffick being finiſhed, ſhe, who was to receive
the profit thereof, returned ſecretly to her
houſe, and made in few howers that which
was ordained her. But Hell is too weak to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow
a party, which Heaven ſupporteth:
Its artifices could nothing againſt a ſimplicity,
which the Providence of a God governeth, nor
the flatteries of a woman, nor the drinks of
an Apothecary, nor the Characters of a Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cereſſe,
could corrupt <hi>Joſeph.</hi> He remained
firm in the midſt of his perſecutions, his
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:119982:51"/>
heart burned not but like the <hi>Seraphins,</hi> his
ſpirit remained clean from filthy thoughts, his
imagination it ſelf received not any evil color.
The love of his God made him to hate his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe;
and becauſe he could not pleaſe him
if he were not innocent, he indevoured to
diſpleaſe her, in refuſing to be culpable. So
generous a conſtancy ſhould cauſe confuſion
and coldneſſe in this <hi>Cyrene,</hi> and vanquiſh ſo
many foul importunities; but a paſſion ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
ſtops it ſelf, but in the precipice, where it
muſt fall. When reaſon ſpeaks unto it, ſhe is
not heard, becauſe it hath no ear: When
prudence ſhews it its duty, it deſpiſeth it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
it hath not the force to acquit it ſelf
thereof. When one repreſents it its puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
it mocketh thereat, becauſe it believes
them not. It will not be healed, becauſe it
thinks not it ſelf to be ſick.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cyrene</hi> obſtinately perſevere no more, you
cannot bend this young man: you will loſe
him abſolutely, if you indevour longer to gain
him: Commonly thoſe that will give love
by force, cauſe nothing but averſion. This
impudent purſued, and as if ſhe had ill orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
her artifices, ſhe began them again. She
returned to her eyes, and to her carriages, ſhe
ſtudied new geſtures, and ſought out counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances
more laſcivious. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> guard your ſelf,
behold the laſt and moſt dangerous of your
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:119982:52"/>
combats; if you yield, your laſt victory is
loſt. Your brothers are not your cruelleſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies,
this perſecution ſurpaſſeth theirs in
malice; the more ſweetneſſe ſhe hath, the leſſe
aſſurance you ought to have; if ſhe flatters,
ſhe will deſtroy: if ſhe ſpeak pleaſingly to you,
ſhe inforceth her ſelf to ſeduce. The praiſes
of this woman are more to be feared then the
calumnies of <hi>Iſſachar,</hi> and her allurements more
redoubtable then the hatred of <hi>Simeon;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
thoſe ruine their love, whereas theſe
pretend to corrupt your vertue; becauſe thoſe
endevour only to put you into diſgrace with
<hi>Jacob,</hi> and theſe deſire to draw the anger of
God upon you; becauſe thoſe have not put
you but into a Ceſtern, and this here hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign
to open Hell unto you. Laſtly, the worſt
effect of thoſe could only ſeparate your life
from your body, and the moſt deplorable
misfortune of theſe is to ſeparate your ſoul
from God.</p>
            <p>It is not unto <hi>Joſeph</hi> that it is neceſſary to
repreſent all theſe reaſons, the inclination that
he hath unto good fortifies him more then our
diſcourſes. Let us conſider this couragious
young man, his vertue deſerves to be regarded
in this encounter. <hi>Potiphar</hi> was to aſſiſt at the
Feaſt of the great God <hi>Apis;</hi> to render his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion
more glorious, he would that all his
Family ſhould accompany him thither. <hi>Joſeph</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:119982:52"/>
who was not accuſtomed to adore the Calves,
found a pretext, which ſeemed to oblige him
to ſtay at home. <hi>Cyrene</hi> who ſaw ſo fair an
occaſion would not loſe it, feigning then ſome
indiſpoſition; her husband, who loved her ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly,
commanded her to keep her bed. Oh
what a dangerous beaſt is a ſubtile woman, and
what means ſhe hath to diſſemble when ſhe goes
about it. Would you believe that <hi>Potiphars</hi>
wife ſeemed to bring much reſiſtance to do a
thing, which ſhe deſired with paſſion; ſhee
ſighed ſo tenderly, that one would have belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
that ſhe would dye of devotion, and that
they ſhould be conſtrained to carry her to the
Tomb, if they led her not to the Temple. She
muſt notwithſtanding conſent to the will of her
husband, which ſhe did more through incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,
then duty, and keeping with her one
only of her women, ſhe commanded the others
to follow her daughter. As <hi>Potiphar</hi> was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted,
and that ſhe imagined the ſolemnity
was at the point, which might aſſure her, ſhe
commanded her Gentlewoman to call the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendant:
This Confident, who was inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted,
went readily to his Chamber, and ſaid
unto him that my Lady would ſpeak with him.
Poor <hi>Joſeph,</hi> diſcover you not this plot? per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
you not this gin? His innocence is not
ſubtile enough to ſuſpect evil intentions in a
ſick perſon. He ran preſently, and found his
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:119982:53"/>
Miſtreſſe half out of her bed, who entertained
him with certain things, of which I deſire you
ſhould not have the thought. At laſt theſe
words not able to perſwade this generous heart,
ſhe ſeiſed on his garment, and preſſed him with
kindneſſes that ſeemed to force him. Our yong
man, who knew well that the victory of this
enemy conſiſted in the flight, left his garment
in the hands of this Infamous, and got to the
ſtairs. <hi>Cyrene</hi> not able to ſuffer this contempt,
changed all her love into hatred, and cryed
out with all her ſtrength for help; being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaved
of the ſhame which ſhe ſhould have, as
well as of her clothes, ſhe would cover her ſelf
with the Cloak of an Innocent, who could
not ward her. Oh how ingenious is fortune
when ſhe will afflict any one!</p>
            <p>As <hi>Joſeph</hi> was on the midſt of the ſtairs, he
met his Maſter, who was returned from
the Temple upon ſome neceſſity. <hi>Potiphar</hi>
ſeeing him without hat, all troubled, and out
of breath; on the other ſide hearing his wife
cry outright, that they ſhould ſtop that Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour,
he conceived a violent ſuſpicion againſt
his innocence. They ſeiſed him, and at the
ſame time led him into his Miſtreſſe chamber,
who held yet his garment in her hands: As
ſoon as ſhe perceived her husband, ſhe ſaid,
in ſhewing the ſpoils of that enemy, that ſhe
loved too much: Truly, Sir, behold the fair
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:119982:53"/>
fruits of the confidence which you have of
that ſlaves fidelity: It was not enough for
him to be prodigal of your goods, if he inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured
not to defile your bed, and to blaſt
ſhamefully my reputation. Scarce were you
departed, but this Perfidious came to make to
me a requeſt, the ſole thought whereof fills me
with confuſion; but having not found that
facility in me which he imagined, he indeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
to draw by violence, what he could not
obtain with my conſent. Behold the marks of
his impudence, which you muſt puniſh, if you
will not have me dye. This word ended, <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene</hi>
feigning that grief overcame her, left her
ſelf to fall backward, with all the ſigns that
might be to deceive, and make a diffidency be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved.</p>
            <p>I leave you to think what rage jealouſie kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
in the heart of <hi>Potiphar,</hi> what cruelty this
rage inſpired him with, what revenge this
choler meditated. One death is not enough
to puniſh an evil thought, which he never had;
he would have him to live an Age, if he had
the means, to make him to dye every day.
What (ſaid he) ingrateful Viper, is it thus
that thou acknowledgeſt ſo many benefits,
which thou haſt never merited? May be that
thou wouldſt puniſh me for having put my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours
into his hands that would raviſh my glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry?
The effect of this outragious deſign, was
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:119982:54"/>
it the affair, that kept thee at home, or the
pretence of that painted piety, which hath ſo
long deceived our ſimplicity? Oh I will make
thee to feel that a ſlave cannot do groſſer faults,
nor have greater temerities, then to have a
mind to bee Maſter. Drag hence this Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</p>
            <p>They led him away without reſiſtance, chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
rather that his innocence ſuffer, then to ſee
<hi>Cyrene</hi> juſtly afflicted. They ſtriped this chaſt
young man; he permitted that they ſhould take
away his clothes, but not his ſhame: They
offended him with ſharp words; he held his
peace, but more through diſcretion,
then want of courage. They tore him with
ſcourges of the whip, the blood ſtreamed down
his body, and ſome tears from his eyes; but he
kept all the conſtancy in a great ſoul. They
diſcovered his bones through the violence of
his dolours; he deſired not to live, he feared
only that death would not finiſh the occaſion of
his merit. At laſt they put this poor innocent
in a condition, which would have given more
compaſſion then love to his Miſtreſſe. That
face which poſſeſſed ſo many attractions, was
all disfigured; his eyes which could convey
innocent flames into hearts, have not lights e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough
to ſee. That body all made of Lillies,
and which appeared rather ſnow then white,
was no more but a ſpectacle of horrour for the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:119982:54"/>
wicked, and a ſubject of pity for the good.
Would to God that all thoſe effeminates,
whom the Cloth of <hi>Holland</hi> hurteth, that thoſe
wantons, who cannot ſleep but upon the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure,
that thoſe infamous Ravens whom luſt
keeps always in breath, could ſee our <hi>Joſeph</hi> in
this pitiful eſtate. I would ſay unto them, this
young man whom you ſee is not tyed to this
pillar, for being convicted of any ſhameful
crime; but for not being able to love any thing
but vertue: Learn of him the reſiſtance that
we muſt bring to an evil action, and how farre
forth our fidelity muſt go. Say not, that it is
impoſſible for you to ſuffer that which he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured,
I do not believe that they have perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
you yet to the blood; and though they
ſhould, your delicacy would not excuſe you,
ſince <hi>Joſeph</hi> was not of the Village. His birth
owes nothing unto yours; his education had
nothing of the Countrey; his blood was ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile;
his age invited him to the pleaſures that
deſtroy you. The faireſt temptations come to
ſeek him; he had no need to corrupt the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity
of a Maid, both by money, and by artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces:
He could only but deſire, and have, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,
and enjoy; and yet O miracle of purity!
he remained firm in an age where all the world
is ſhaken, inflexible in a condition, wherein
the moſt part of men do bend, and victorious
in an occaſion, where no body fights without
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:119982:55"/>
difficulty, and overcomes not without dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage.</p>
            <p>Strange thing, my dear Auditours, that Love
ſhould produce hatred. Truly if we may
judge of the conſanguinity by the reſemblance
of the humours, we ſhould conclude that theſe
two paſſions are enemies rather then allies; it is
for all that too true; that his fair Mother puts
ſometimes this ugly daughter into nature. I
confeſſe that the birth thereof is monſtrous,
and appeareth but ſeldome, it appeareth not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding;
and though that it be difficult to
ſee the reaſon thereof, it is eaſie to ſee the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples.
<hi>Cyrene</hi> loved <hi>Joſeph</hi> tenderly, and
now ſhe perſecutes him: I wonder not at
that; that which ſurpriſeth me, is that her
hate ſhould ſpring from her love. The Trees
thruſt not forth always the boughs, which are
natural to them. The Animals bear ſometimes
baſtard-young, and which are ſtrange. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
doubt this happeneth, when the principle
of theſe productions is mingled. But how
though can hate be born of love? Love pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth
but love, when it concurs with the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem
of its object; but if it joins it ſelf to its
contempt, it conceives hatred. When we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
they fly us, becauſe they deſpiſe us, our
paſſion revolts, and in ſtead of being ſweet, it
is embittered. What marvel though the wife
of <hi>Potiphar</hi> perſecute <hi>Joſeph?</hi> In the firſt
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:119982:55"/>
place ſhe revengeth her love, which ſhe ſees re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected;
Secondly, ſhe hides her impurity, which
is diſcovered. Voluptuouſneſſe not able to
content this paſſion, which ſeeketh but plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,
choler inſpires her with rage, which che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth
nothing but blood. It is a dangerous
Monſter, an heart that deſireth to be loved,
and which one cannot love. I apprehend but
lamentable things for our ſlave, ſince he refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
to love his Miſtreſſe.</p>
            <p>Whileſt I am diverted from my ſubject, I
perceived not that they took <hi>Joſeph</hi> away; let
us endevour to find him again, and not loſe
one alone of his good examples. But alas! I
ſee him in a priſon, where the light enters not,
but when the door is open; I ſee him loaden
with Irons: I ſee him amongſt Thieves and
Robberss: I ſee him in the horrours of a
cruel Captivity. He hath carried notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
all his patience into this infamous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trait,
all the vertues would accompany him
thither; and though the fatal ſpectacles of
death, which he had before his eyes, might
ſhake a great courage, his ſhewed in the ſereni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
of his countenance, that he had not learned
to yield unto mean afflictions. His cruel do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours
could not make him to confeſſe by one
ſole ſigh that he ſuffered, nor that his patience
was aſſaulted: He ſpake not, but through the
praiſes which he gave unto God. His diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:119982:56"/>
made nothing appear of an abated courage;
if he complained ſometimes, it was only to
ſay,</p>
            <p>O my God! who thought thou hadſt the
ſecrets to change puniſhments into pleaſures;
and make ſweetneſſe to be found in the bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
gall? I begin to blame my little experience,
and to wiſh ill to the ignorances of my youth.
When the cruelty of my brothers made me a
ſlave, I thought my fortune ruined; when that
blinded man began to look upon me favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly,
with <hi>Potiphar,</hi> I praiſed my good fortune;
&amp; I ſee now that that firſt accident was the firſt
ſource of my joyes, and that happy beginning
the fatal cauſe of my ruine. It is at this preſent
that I know the advantages of misfortune, and
the dangers of proſperity. My vertue appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
too fair, hath been tempted by my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
and cheriſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d of my Miſtreſſe: Their
hate hath conſerved me, her love hath almoſt
deſtroyed me: O deſirable chains, how I love
you! Sweet Providence, how I adore you
with all my heart! I cheriſh you, precious
chains, becauſe you are that which ſettles my
ſalvation, becauſe you are that which renders
my vertues firm and immoveable. If you load
my body, you adorn my ſoul. The torment
which you give me, ſhall not make me re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce
the glory which you gain me. I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore
thee, amiable Providence of my God, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:119982:56"/>
as thou haſt conducted me upon the
thorns without hurting me; for that thou
haſt made me to tread upon the roſes without
ſeducing me; and above all, I adore thee for
that thou haſt brought me here by thoſe ways
wholly deſirable, ſince they put my little ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
in a place where it may conſerve it ſelf,
and not be deſtroyed. I confeſſe that the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings
which I taſte, are not deſired, but it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
they are not known: For my part, whom
thy goodneſſe favoureth with this important
knowledge, I conceive ſo perfectly the merit
thereof, that I begge no more of thee, O my
God, but that thou wouldſt continue me my
pains and my affliction, to the end to prolong
my joyes and my contentments. I will ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r
all my life, provided that it be with innocence,
and that thou wouldſt receive ſome ſatisfaction
from my languiſhments.</p>
            <p>Behold near the very diſcourſe of <hi>Joſeph,</hi>
whileſt he had cauſe to complain, and it was
put to the teſt, if vertue could be grieved: that
of this illuſtrious Captive being wholly cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious,
imployed it ſelf rather to combat the
vices, which are found in priſons, then to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore
poorly his condition. Who admires not
that thoſe perſons who touch death almoſt,
and who have always the gibbets and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
before their eyes, ſhould make the place
of the impenitence the ſchool of an evil life!
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:119982:57"/>
Ordinarily the priſon is not more filled with
ordure, then with vices, ſin makes the moſt
deplorable miſery. Impatience, murmurings,
ſwearing, and blaſphemies are taught here as a
Science proper to that eſtate. <hi>Joſeph</hi> wanted
no wit, but he had not any to retain that leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon;
On the contrary, taking the liberty
which vertue ſhould always have even in Irons,
and Chains, he corrected ſweetly their evil
life, making them to apprehend that the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
Juſtice would abandon them to the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane,
if their repentance appeaſed not its
choler. It was by ſuch like inſtructions, that
he changed theſe ſouls of dirt, and made rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable
creatures of thoſe that were not ſo.</p>
            <p>The vertue of this new priſoner being profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
to the Gaoler, he was ſoon beloved of
him: and though commonly this ſort of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
have ſouls of Iron, yet <hi>Joſephs</hi> wrought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
him ſo, that he gain'd himſelf an opinion
of his merit. The Gaoler viſited him often,
and took a ſingular pleaſure in his converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:
But behold what made up the good opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
which he had of him, and put him well
forward in credit; the Gaoler being one day
entred into the Chamber of our holy Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch,
<hi>Joſeph</hi> perceived his ſadneſſe, and as he
was gracious, he ſaid unto him: My Maſter,
me thinks that you have not to day your plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant
humour? Truly (replyed the Gaoler)
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:119982:57"/>
I have no cauſe to be very well content, my
poor wife ſuffers ſuch cruel pains ſince yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day
evening, that he muſt not bee her husband
that can ſee her without pity: I fear that this
child-bed will be her laſt, and that the throws
which labour her, will thruſt her into the
grave. At theſe words <hi>Joſeph</hi> remembring
himſelf of his mother, who dyed of ſuch tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
beſtowed ſome tears on the affliction of
his Maſter, and to contribute to his comfort
ſomething more then compaſſion, he offered
him certain black ſtones, and ſaid unto him.
My Maſter, carry readily this ſuccour to your
wife, and I promiſe you that ſhe ſhall no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
uſe it, but her pain ſhall be appeaſed.</p>
            <p>The Gaoler without diſputing the quality
of thoſe ſtones, took them to carry them to
the ſick, who had not ſcarce handled them,
but ſhe was happily brought to bed of a ſon.</p>
            <p>I obſerved the place where <hi>Joſeph</hi> took theſe
ſtones, but I have not told you that God had
given them in favour of <hi>Rah<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l,</hi> the vertue to
facilitate the Couches of thoſe, who were in
travel with child, which many writers have
obſerved. Doubt not that this benefit acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
not the good will of the Gaoler to his
priſoner, his wife her ſelf would ſee her
preſerver, and thank him for the aſſiſtance
which ſhee had received from his charitie:
From that time forward it was an ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:119982:58"/>
thing to ſee <hi>Joſeph</hi> at his Maſters Table,
who had ſuch a confidence of his fidelity,
that he truſted the other priſoners to his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct.
Admire you not the goodneſſe of our
God, who delivers his ſervant ſweetly from
miſery; but attend yet a little, and you ſhall
confeſſe, that it belongs but to his Providence
to unwinde the Labyrinth of our misfortunes.
There was in this priſon two Lords of <hi>Phara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ohs</hi>
houſe, the one was his chief Baker, and
the other his chief Butler, both of them faln
with his diſgrace into a priſon. I know not
for a truth, the cauſe of their misfortune; but
if you will believe the <hi>Rabbines,</hi> who pleaſe
themſelves with fables, we ſhall learn from
their dreams a fair inſtruction. Some of theſe
Sages aſſure, that <hi>Pharaoh</hi> being one day at
Table, one ſerv'd him up bread, wherein he
found a little grain of ſand, and a Cup of
wine, wherein there was a flye drowned.
This Prince extreamly incenſed againſt them,
who ſhould have care to foreſee theſe diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,
commanded that they ſhould be thrown
into the bottome of a Dungeon, to repent
themſelves there at leiſure of their negligence.
I believe that this is but an invention of their
wit, yet we have here a perfect Image of the
inconſtancy of Princes in their affection. It is
too much that a Flye paſſe before their eyes, to
change them. The leaſt fault provokes them;
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:119982:58"/>
who is not their Slave, is a Malefactor. If a
Courtier be not always in humour to ſerve, if
he adore not all their thoughts, he is culpable
enough to be puniſhed; he muſt flatter, or pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh.
They drive him from the houſe, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
often from the world; at leaſt a ſudden
anger pays a long ſervitude with death, or
with baniſhment.</p>
            <p>To return to <hi>Joſeph,</hi> it is certain that hee
brought a particular care to acquit himſelf of
the charge which was committed to him. He
viſited often theſe poor wretches, endevouring
to render their condition better, and more
ſupportable by the ſweetneſſe of his uſage.</p>
            <p>There is I know not what pleaſure to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
our miſeries, and to put our diſpleaſures
into the boſome of a friend: This comfort
being eaſie, our priſoners uſed it, entertaining
one another with their fortunes, even ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
with their dreams.</p>
            <p>As <hi>Joſeph</hi> had found them one morning
more ſad then ordinary, he ſate down by them,
and asked them what cauſe they had to be me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy:
Seigneur <hi>Ioſeph</hi> (replyed the But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler)
I have for ſome time ſweetned my evils as
well as I could, and ſuffered them with ſome
patience. But ſince three or four days, as if my
evil would exulcerate, I feel new touches of
dolour. The day puts but objects of horrour
before mine eyes; the night forms me phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſmes
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:119982:59"/>
of all her ſhadows, and fills my ſoul
with affright as well as the world with dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.
This very night I had a dream, which
gave as many fears as I gave it divers interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.
It ſeemed unto me, that I ſaw a Vine
ſtock that divided it ſelf into three branches,
loaden with very fair grapes, which I preſſed
into the Kings Cup to preſent it him. I took
an extream pleaſure to ſerve my Prince, when
a noiſe awaked me.</p>
            <p>Sir, (replyed <hi>Ioſeph</hi>) your dream need not
to be longer, to be good: The conjecture is
ſo favourable, that I fear not to tell it you.
The three branches, which you have ſeen, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>note
that you ſhall be yet three days unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate;
after which, you ſhall enter again into
the good graces of your Prince, by the favour
of his good graces into all your Honours. I
cannot deceive you longer then three days; if
you find me a liar, count me a Villain; but if
the event prove true, I deſire no other recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence
of you, but that you will ſpeak a good
word for me unto <hi>Pharoah,</hi> and procure me my
liberty. You ſuppoſe to oblige herein a Slave,
but you ſhall oblige the ſon of the chief of the
<hi>Hebrews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This good Prophecie pleaſed ſo much the
chief Baker, that he believed to have as hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily
dreamed as his companion, and promiſed
himſelf by the reſemblance of the viſions, an
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:119982:59"/>
event equal unto his. I thought (ſaid he) that
I carried this night upon my head three baskets
full of all ſorts of bak'd meats, and of moſt
exquiſite Viands. I know not what preſage I
may draw from an accident during this occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
Though theſe delicates were not for the
birds, they eat up notwithſtanding all that
which was expoſed to them. <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired
not to ſay but good words, expreſſed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough
by his reſervedneſſe, that this dream
promiſed no good unto him who had had it.
Notwithſtanding the importunity of the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,
conſtrained him at laſt to tell him, that
he had ſeen his misfortune, and that the King
would cauſe him to be hanged within three
days, leaving his body on the Gibbet to ſerve
for food to the Crowes. If this explication
was believed or rejected, I cannot ſay; but I
am certain that the interpretation ſaw nothing
that was not found true, and that the ſucceſſe
proved its experience.</p>
            <p>We have a little to obſerve, that the dreams had
ſhewed to our ſlave ſome one of his adventures,
the encounter of thoſe which we come to
hear, was one of the cauſes of his good fortune.
It was hereby that the good fortune of <hi>Ioſeph</hi>
began, becauſe that God willing to diſpoſe
<hi>Pharaoh</hi> to the greatneſſe of his faithful ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,
he ſent him two Viſions, which buſied
all the wits of <hi>Egypt,</hi> without giving content
to the King.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:119982:60"/>
One day this Prince keeping Court and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen
Table to his ſubjects, related unto them
what he had dreamed the precedent night;
but as he found no body that could give him
the knowledge thereof, the Butler, whom pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity
had made to forget the benefits of <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,</hi>
bethought himſelf at laſt of him, and
of his experience. Without fearing the blame
of ſo black an ingratitude, he ſaid to his King,
Sir, in putting your Majeſty in minde of my
priſon, I muſt neceſſarily confeſſe me crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall,
ſince your juſtice cannot fail. This con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration
might oblige another, but me to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal
a good advice, for fear to repeal the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance
of an infamy; but I who am ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
glad to confeſſe my crime to publiſh your
clemency, and who hold my conſervation
more aſſured in your good will, then in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
it ſelf, am not careful to hide from you a
thing, which may be advantagious to your
contentments. When I was in the priſon, from
whence your goodneſſe delivered me, I met
there a young <hi>Hebrew,</hi> who upon the diſcourſe
which I made him of one of my dreams, aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
me of all the events which I ſaw in my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune.
I think, if it pleaſe your Majeſty to
ſend for him, that he will declare unto you the
true ſenſe of your dreams. The King who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired
paſſionately to be cleared upon this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,
commanded preſently that hee ſhould
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:119982:60"/>
come forth out of priſon. Our ſlave never
thought himſelf ſo much in a dream, as when
he ſaw a great number of perſons about him,
of whom ſome preſented him rich ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits,
and others cut his hair, that he might
appear before the Prince with decency. When
he was accoutred according as was conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent,
they conducted him towards <hi>Pharaoh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As ſoon as the King perceived him, he judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
by his countenance, that this man was not
made for a ſlave; and after having asked him
many queſtions on his birth, he ſaid unto him,
that one of his Courtiers had given him ſo
good teſtimonies of his knowledge, that he
hoped ſatisfaction from thence. To this, <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,</hi>
who had put himſelf on his knees, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered,
that his capacity was ſo little conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable,
that it would be to deceive himſelf, to
expect great ſuccours from thence; but that he
adored a God, who had too much goodneſſe
to fail him at his need. The King approving
this modeſty, replyed; Friend, I pray thee
not to excuſe thee upon thy ignorance; and
if thou knoweſt the truth, think not that it
ſhall be odious to me, if it be not pleaſing. I
will make more accompt of thy freeneſſe, then
of all the diſguiſes with which thou mayeſt
flatter me. I underſtand that thou canſt divine
the future times by the preſent; tell me then, I
pray thee, what my dreams ſignifie: Perhaps
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:119982:61"/>
the common brute hath already acquainted
thee with them, notwithſtanding that the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances
may not change thy judgement, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
all the particularities thereof. One night
it was repreſented me, that I walked upon the
bank of <hi>Nile,</hi> from whence I ſaw come forth
ſeven fat kine, who afterward went to feed in
the Mariſhes far diſtant from the bank of the
River: And it ſeemed unto me, that I had
never ſeen fairer beaſts then theſe; but whileſt
I conſidered them, I perceived ſeven others
very unlike unto them, for they were ſo lean
that their skin ſcarce covered their bones. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
if they had not had motion, I ſhould
have taken them for Skeletons, ſo anatomis'd
were they; their ribs were ſo apparent, as if
they had been naked. If hunger could appear
to the eyes, and that ſhe could content her ſelf
to feed on ſand, I ſhould have thought to ſee
her under this figure. Whileſt <hi>I</hi> admir'd the
extream meagerneſſe of thoſe beaſts, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan
to run towards the firſt with ſo much
ſwiftneſſe, as if rage had provoked them. That
which gave me moſt aſtoniſhment, was to ſee
that almoſt in a moment, they devoured theſe
fat kine, without ſo much as one that eſcaped.
This is not yet the end of my viſions, for at
the ſame howre <hi>I</hi> ſaw grow up as it were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
my feet a ſtalk of Corn having ſeven ears
rank and goodly, but as if they were to run
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:119982:61"/>
the ſame fortune that the beaſts of my firſt
dream did; I ſaw ſeven others ſo blaſted and
withered, that they dryed up the others ſo
quickly, that one would have almoſt believed
that their preſence made them diſſolve or va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh,
rather then periſh.</p>
            <p>As the King had ended the recital of his
dreams, <hi>Joſeph,</hi> who was very attentive to this
diſcourſe, took the word, and ſaid unto him:
Sir, ſince it pleaſeth your Majeſty to permit a
poor ſlave to ſpeak in your preſence, and that
you deſire to hear the truth, although it ſhould
not be advantagious unto you, I will tell you
freely, that your two dreams have not but one
and the ſame ſenſe, and that God is willing to
confirm you by this double viſion in a belief
which I will give you. Your Majeſty is not
ignorant that the fertility of <hi>Egypt</hi> comes not
but from the overflowing of the River that
waters it, and that his waters diffuſe not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
ſo much to cover her with her flood, as
with riches. Moreover, you know that the
height of his inundation is the meaſure of her
abundance, and of her want, from whence
in my opinion is ſprung that common ſaying
of your people, that ſix cubits of flood mark
but her miſeries, and that fifteen or ſixteen
ſhew the delights thereof. This being ſo, I
hold for aſſured, that the ſeven firſt kine ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie
ſeven years of unparallel'd plenty. And
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:119982:62"/>
on the contrary, that the others repreſent the
ſterility that is to follow them. Two circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances
make me this interpretation reaſonable
enough: The firſt is, that your Majeſty hath
ſeen theſe beaſts come forth out of the ſame
place, from whence proceeds your abundance,
and that they ſcattered them very far into the
Country. From whence we may gather that
the River will effuſe it ſelf very far into the
plain, to carry thither the fertility. Thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
ſeven lean kine, being not far from the
bank of <hi>Nile,</hi> ſhew that his inundation ſhall
not extend it ſelf farther, and conſequently all
the reſt of the Land ſhall remain barren; in
ſuch ſort that theſe laſt years ſhall conſume the
abundance of the former. I will not be thought
true, but by the event of my preſage, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
if your Majeſty would take a very
profitable counſel, I could wiſh that you would
appoint a man, who ſhould have the Intenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy
of your Granaries, and the power to build
new throughout all the Towns of your Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire.
And there (if I may be believed here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in)
let him lay up the fifth part of the grain,
which ſhall be ſuperfluous in the former years,
to ſupply the want of the following years.</p>
            <p>It cannot be ſaid with how much applauſe
this advice was received of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> if it bee
not that the honours and benefits which he did
him were not ſufficient teſtimonies. Having
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:119982:62"/>
then praiſed his prudence, he gave him his Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net,
and then taking off a great Chain of gold
from his neck, he put it upon <hi>Joſeph's.</hi> He
commanded likewiſe that there ſhould be
brought him a garment of ſilk, and his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
beſt Chariot prepared for him, ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
all <hi>Egypt</hi> to have him in the ſame venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
that they had his own perſon, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
no more love from his ſubjects, then he
deſired thereof unto <hi>Joſeph.</hi> Behold then our
ſlave, Vice-Roy of the moſt flouriſhing Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces
of <hi>Africk,</hi> and acknowledged preſerver
of the people of the Eaſt. Behold, how all
the Court of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> conducted him through
the Town, raiſed upon a Chariot of triumph.
The Heraulds cryed, that every one ſhould bow
the knee before him; no body failed to render
him this honour, for the will of the Prince,
and the natural graces of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> conſtrained
them to this homage.</p>
            <p>What can theſe petty ſpirits ſay now, who
cannot but murmure, and who blame all the
conducts of God, which they cannot compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend?
Will they complain that he leaves his
friends to ſuffer, ſeeing he abaſes them not, but
to exalt them? Heretofore they had pity of
<hi>Joſeph,</hi> who is it that bears him not envy now?
They fled his miſeries, who deſires not his
honours? The <hi>Hebrewes</hi> perſecuted him, all
<hi>Egypt</hi> honours him: His brothers took from
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:119982:63"/>
him his Robe, <hi>Pharaoh</hi> gives him the Royal
Mantle; <hi>Potiphar</hi> puts manicles on his hands
and neck, <hi>Pharaoh</hi> adorns him with a Chain
of Gold: He offers him a Scepter for that
Sheephook w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> he handled. We have ſeen him
in a Ceſtern, and in the darkneſſe of a priſon;
at this hower the Marble and Porphyrie is not
matter rich enough to build him Palaces. Oh
Providence of my God! How much better is
it to follow thee amongſt the thorns and briars,
ſince thou leadeſt to felicity, then the favour of
men, ſince that conducts only to the Abyſmes.</p>
            <p>Whileſt <hi>Joſeph</hi> triumphed in the Palaces, and
Streets of <hi>Memphis, Potiphar,</hi> who knew no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
yet of his fortune, met him in the glory
of this pomp, which made him adored of the
<hi>Egyptians.</hi> If ever a Malefactour charged with
many enormous crimes, was ſurpriſed with
the preſence of his Judges, it was but an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage
of his aſtoniſhment; but the admiration
was not the only paſſion of his ſoul, for the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory
of what was paſſed gave him ſome preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
fears; he remembred that he had firmly
perſecuted him, who could then puniſh him.
The ſweetneſſe of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſeemed to give him
all kind of aſſurance; but the crime whereof
he had ſuſpected him, appeared unto him ſo
black, that he could not hope for pardon. I
leave you to judge if the diverſity of theſe
thoughts did put irreſolution into his deſign.
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:119982:63"/>
Having notwithſtanding ſlipped himſelf out of
the preſſe into his houſe, he related the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperities,
and the power of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to <hi>Cyrene,</hi>
who conceived the ſame fears that her husband
did. It was at this time that the apprehenſion
of death was ſtronger then that of infamy;
for this poor woman conſidering rather in <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi>
a pitiful Saviour, then a rigorous Judge,
had more confidence of his goodneſſe, then fear
of his juſtice. Upon this reſolution ſudden
enough, but for all that judicious, ſhe caſt her
ſelf at her husbands feet, confeſſed unto him
the artifices which had made <hi>Ioſeph</hi> guilty, and
beſought him to pardon a fault, which ſhee
would never have done, if ſhe had not ſeen the
moſt amiable of all men. Beſides that, ſhe
would waſh away this ſtain with her blood, and
offer her ſelf to the vengeance of the Vice-Roy
for to free him thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Potiphar</hi> was much aſtoniſhed to hear the
practiſes of his wife, notwithſtanding her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grets
pacified him, and the abundance of her
tears drowned all the remains of choler, which
might yet be in a body already cold with age.
Jealouſie, which ſees but the preſent, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents
not the paſs'd with the ſame colours as
formerly in the heat of his firſt amours. The
honeſty which he had always obſerved in <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene,</hi>
perſwaded him eaſily, that though ſhee
had been conſtrained to love <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> ſhe would
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:119982:64"/>
never have been ſo much as ſolicited to look
upon another. Behold him then reſolved to
go to the Vice-Roy of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and by the
confeſſion of his errour, to implore his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.
But who can believe the Careſſes which
<hi>Joſeph</hi> made to his old Maſter, and to his wife,
when he ſaw them at his knees, to finde there
the pardon of their fault, or to ſubmit their
life to the rigour of his juſtice? Fear had
painted the image of death upon their viſage,
and ſo tyed their tongue, that all what they
could ſay, was to confeſſe themſelves crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals.
Then our Patriarch exerciſing the firſt
effect of his power upon the reſentment of his
injuries, raiſed them, and by the abundance of
his tears, witneſſed to them, that he had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
but love, and tenderneſſe in his heart.</p>
            <p>My friends, (ſaid he unto them) I conjure
you to forget what is paſs'd, and to expect as
much of my affection for the future, as if I
were your ſon. I am obliged thereunto both
by duty, and by inclination. It is to you that
I owe my proſperities; it is with you that I
will divide them: Perhaps if I had not been
miſerable, I ſhould not be now happy. If a
ſtorm ſhould drive me unto the Port, I ſhould
bleſſe it, and I ſhould love him that would cure
me, would he empoiſon me. You have failed,
the one through too much zeal, the other
through too much love: Theſe two perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:119982:64"/>
are too amiable for me to diſoblige: <hi>I</hi>
pardon that exceſſe to the weakneſſe of our
nature. I chuſe rather to believe that my miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes
were arriv'd me from the Providence
of God, then from the malice of men. For
my part, who am the ſubject of all theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancies
of fortune, ſo far am I from keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
any reſentment againſt you, that I deſire
henceforward to have no better friends then
my firſt Maſters. The truth of my words ſhall
be known by the effects upon all occaſions
wherein you ſhall employ me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joſeph</hi> no ſooner finiſhed his diſcourſe, but
he began his liberalities, offering to <hi>Potiphar</hi>
a Chain of Gold, and to his wife a Roſe of
Diamonds; his daughter was not forgotten,
for he ſent her by one of his Gentlemen, two
rich Pendants for her ears, which equalled not
for all that the price of his affection. Since
this firſt ſight he never ceaſed to oblige them, as
if he had deſign to do them as much good, as
he had received evil from them.</p>
            <p>A little while after this interview, death ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed
<hi>Cyrene,</hi> as if ſhe had not ſtayed but to
ſee her Innocent, to take away her life. After
her deceaſe, <hi>Potiphar</hi> was capable of the chief
dignity of <hi>Egypt;</hi> he was poſſeſſour thereof,
ſince he was furniſhed therewith at the recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation
of the Vice-Roy. <hi>Heliopolis</hi> ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
the ſame honors to the God <hi>Mnenis,</hi> as
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:119982:65"/>
               <hi>Memphis</hi> did to the God <hi>Apis;</hi> and to ſpeak
the truth, there is no more reaſon to honour
the beaſts in one place then in another. It was
then the dignity of the high Prieſt, which <hi>Poti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phar</hi>
exerciſed in that Town of the Sun; and
though <hi>Joſeph</hi> would rather have ſeen the
Calves at the ſhambles, then upon the Altars,
he judged it fitter to put this ſuperſtition into
the hands of his Maſter, then to charge ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
therewith, becauſe he knew him more ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable
to deride it. The care which he had to
ruine the Idols, juſtified the care which he took
in appearance to eſtabliſh them. It was a truce
which he made with the gods of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and
not a peace that he concluded; he gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
leiſure to think of their deſtruction with
ſafety.</p>
            <p>Let us leave this high Prieſt departed with all
his family, to go exerciſe his charge, and let
us ſtay to conſider the conduct of our Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant.
I know that <hi>Philon</hi> repreſents us him as
the example of a faithful Miniſter, and that a
great Cardinal makes him the Idea of his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch;
but I can ſay that he had ſomething
more then the qualities which are neceſſary to
the one and the other, ſince he wanted not any
perfection that might compleat a man. He
needed not to ſeek the model of a wiſe Favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite
out of himſelf; the perfect Courtier was in
his perſon. He poſſeſſed the heart of his Maſter,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:119982:65"/>
but he managed it not but to bring it to doe
good to all the world; ſo that his hands were
but the publick Conduits of his Princes favors.
He could take every one in his humour, hee
would buy thoſe that would not give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves:
The moſt rude and ſavage ſpirits found
ſweetneſſe in his, and if the enormity of the
crimes required ſome rigour from him, it was
but with regret that he was juſt, loving better
to correct vice by the repentance then by the
deſpair of the guilty. All <hi>Egypt</hi> was no more
but a great family, of which he was the father,
procuring with an incredible care that abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance
and delights might be there without
luxury. This deſign ſucceeded to him ſo well,
that they muſt goe more then an hundred miles,
to finde one miſerable or one vicious. For as
felicity was eſtabliſhed in this happy Country,
the good manners met here alſo: all the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
vertues reigned there, excepting thoſe which
cannot exerciſe themſelves but in misfortune,
or which ſuppoſe imperfections and defects in
their objects. Never did policy arrive more
perfectly to her end, which is to make as many
happy as ſhe hath ſubjects, then at that time,
having the wiſdome of <hi>Joſeph</hi> for ſoul and
Intelligence. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> taſted this good fortune;
for he was loved of his people, he was feared
of his enemies. The ſtrangers could not give
more ſolid foundation to their repoſe, then to
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:119982:66"/>
gain them the good will of <hi>Ioſeph.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it is time to admire one of the miracles
of the world, and to conſider theſe prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious
Pyramids, which hide whole Provinces
with their ſhadow. I am not ignorant that
there are ſome Writers, who aſſure us, that theſe
proud Obeliſques were the monuments of the
Kings of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and that theſe excellent works
were made but to cover magnificently duſt and
aſhes. I know well alſo, that there are other
ſome, who make our <hi>Ioſeph</hi> the Authour of
them, and that they ſhould be the publick
Granaries, which he cauſed to be built in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
Town, principally at <hi>Memphis,</hi> and about
<hi>Babylon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whileſt that more then an hundred thouſand
hands were employed about theſe buildings,
there was but the head of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> that laboured,
to ſee if the exe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ution anſwered to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign,
and if the work were as perfect as the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea,
he took leave of the King, and viſited all
<hi>Egypt.</hi> It was during this courſe that he knew
Heaven took care to marry him, and that
God would not that virginity ſhould be lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
one of his vertues. It will not be from our
purpoſe to obſerve the Providence of him,
who diſpoſed thus the will of our Patriarch.</p>
            <p>I have ſaid, that <hi>Potiphar</hi> had a daughter
endowed with a rare and raviſhing beauty, and
whoſe incomparable perfections invited a great
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:119982:66"/>
number of Lords to her ſuit; but though ſhe
gave love to all the world, ſhe took it not from
any perſon. I know not whether ſhe eſteemed
the braveſt of the kingdome unworthy of her
alliance, or if naturally ſhe could not love a
man. At leaſt, might one judge that there
was contempt or inclination in the care which
ſhe took to fly their encounter? Since the time
that her father was retired to <hi>Heliopolis,</hi> ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted
her ſelf to the ſervice of <hi>Diana,</hi> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed
her that ſhe would only then ceaſe to be
a Virgin, when ſhe ſhould ceaſe to be the great
goodeſſe of the Forreſts. This vow was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable
in her opinion, becauſe ſhe knew not
that the falſe idols were mortal things. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
it was, this poor maid ſerved this falſe
Divinity with more Religion, then many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
ſerve the true God, who hath recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
to make himſelf beloved, and puniſhments
to make himſelf feared. The only pleaſure
that ſhe ſought; ſhe found in ſolitude: Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
did ſhe deſire of the Theatres, nor of the
Comedies made her go forth: the dances and
balls, and thoſe other divertiſements of the
Maids, were not a temptation ſtrong enough for
her: Her ſhadow was her moſt ordinary com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion;
but if ſometimes ſhe releaſed her ſelf
of this great ſeverity, ſeven young Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
of her age and humour paſs'd the time
with her. All their employment deriv'd it ſelf
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:119982:67"/>
from Books, or a Garden which was ſeen from
the windows of their abode. Art never ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
a place more pleaſant then that, where
all the delights of <hi>Aſſeneth</hi> were encloſed.</p>
            <p>I would fain deſcribe this fair deſert, ſince
this great Lady took pains to improve it. The
ground of the Platform look'd upon the riſing
Sun, which look'd upon it again with ſo much
complaiſance, that one would have ſaid his
raies had nothing to do in <hi>Egypt,</hi> but to paint
its flowers, and to ripen its fruits. This fair
Star made not gold here, but he infuſed no leſs
favourable influences, then thoſe which are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
for its conception.</p>
            <p>There was in the midſt of the Garden a
Fountain, whoſe waters being received into a
Conduit of white Marble, imparted themſelves
through little gilded Pipes unto all the partiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
as if nature provided againſt the danger
that the Sun might blaſt the flowers in behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
them too long. The Earth feeling it ſelf
touch'd by Virgin-hands, became not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
barren, if it were not in the midſt of the
Alleys, where it bore nothing but ſand. You
would have ſaid, that ſhe reſerved her humour
to form the Violets, the Lillies and the Roſes
for her Miſtreſſe, and that all her occupation
was to obey her. The herbs came where
ſhe deſired, and their complaiſance was ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,
that they ſeemed to fear to be fruitful a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:119982:67"/>
her mind. The Trees were content to
bowe without reſiſtance, conſtraint being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary
to hold their branches, becauſe they
were naturally ſo ſupple, that art laboured not
to accommodate them. To ſee the buſhes form
themſelves into all kind of animals, the Juni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
to ſhape it ſelf into Bears, and the other
Plants to take the figure of Birds, you would
have believed that this fair Magician had chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
the Beaſts into Trees, or that the Trees
were transformed into Beaſts. It was ſhe who
had faſhioned a Chaſſe of Roſemary, and of
Lavander ſo naturally, that you would have
ſworn theſe dogs would be gone, if their roots
had not ſtayed them better then their leaſes. Of
the other ſide the Hares ſtretched themſelves
ſo ardently to the courſe, that they ſeemed to
apprehend their taking. It was ſhe, who had
mingled the windings of a Labyrinth with
ſo much artifice, that the moſt direct would
have gone a great way in a very little ſpace,
and run a whole Country in a Garden-plot.
It was ſhe, who during the moſt cruel rigours
of the Winter, conſerved a little Summer to
ripen the Oranges, and the Citrons, even
when they began to corrupt in other places.
From this Garden, which was but for delights,
one deſcended into a Green, where of one
ſide was nothing to be ſeen but dwarfs, and of
the other but giants. The laſt ſeemed to raiſe
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:119982:68"/>
themſelves above the other Trees, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
their branches to the heat of the Sun, to
the end to cook the firſt-fruits for their Miſtreſs.
The firſt changed themſelves almoſt all into
fruits, witneſſing deſpight that they were too
little to render her great ſervices. But all the
beauty of the flowers was but a weak ray of
thoſe which they endevoured to paint in their
leaves; and the fecundity of the Trees ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
alone that a Virgin is not barren when ſhe
will.</p>
            <p>Behold the exerciſe which employed the
daughter of <hi>Potiphar,</hi> when hee underſtood
that the Vice-Roy came to deſcend to his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace,
to take there his lodging. Doubt not
but this news was pleaſing to him, ſince he held
his fortune from his liberalities, and hoped
the increaſe thereof from his magnificence; for
he had no ſooner received it, but he went
forth to meet this dear gueſt, whom he enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
with thoſe careſſes and reſpects, that
can better be conceived then expreſſed. This
was no more that ſlave, whom they would tear
in pieces: This is no more that perfidious
ſervant, whom he had cauſed to be caſt into
the bottome of a Dungeon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Ioſeph</hi> being arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
at the Palace of <hi>Potiphar,</hi> that fair Nymph
of whom I have ſpoken, came to ſalute him.
I leave the ceremonies of this Interview to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother
Writer, only I cannot conceal that this
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:119982:68"/>
man, who had ſo little fleſh, and who look'd
upon women as if he had been all ſpirit, could
not ſee her without loving her. But ſurely
the flame that warmed him, burnt him not;
his thoughts were pure, as his flame was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent.
There is no need to be a Divine, to
conjecture the correſpondence which he found
in the inclination of <hi>Aſſeneth:</hi> This ſtubborn
beauty who could not love but the flowers,
and who ſought no other converſation but that
of the Trees, acknowledged that <hi>Joſeph</hi> was
too fair not to be loved. Notwithſtanding her
affection was ſo well ordered, that it never
exceeded modeſty; ſo had ſhe not to defend her
ſelf from an Innocent, but rather to receive
the chaſt vows of an <hi>Hero.</hi> It is true, that
thinking her ſelf obliged to <hi>Diana,</hi> ſhe ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured
wiſely to quench the firſt ſparks, for
fear to engage her ſelf in a ſuit which ſhe judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
impoſſible. This was the beginning of the
fair amours of our holy young man, who
knowing that God would have it that <hi>Aſſeneth</hi>
ſhould be his wife; and on the other ſide his
inclination finding it ſelf conformable to the
will of God, reſolved to ſpeak of her marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age
to the high Prieſt. As he walked one af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon
with him, taking him by the hand, he
held him forth this diſcourſe. My dear Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,
(it was the name that he gave him for
the moſt part) perhaps you will think it ſtrange,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:119982:69"/>
I tell you that I have a deſign to ſeek your
daughter, and perhaps will reply, that you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
ſuffer one of your ſlaves ſhould deſire to be
your ſon in law. Notwithſtanding if you
will conſider my preſent condition, without
thinking of that which is paſs'd, I believe you
will not find much preſumption in my deſire,
and I may hope for approbation in your ſpirit.
It is true, that a fortune made up in haſte, as
mine, is not ordinarily aſſured, and that we
ſee as many diſgraced as favoured. So that
it is not upon this conſideration that I ask your
conſent; I have better reaſons to make you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
of my ſuit, without owing any thing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
favour. I am deſcended from a family,
which will be no ſhame unto yours. My birth
merited a better fortune then thoſe Irons, which
by diſaſter, or rather by the Providence of
God, I met with in your houſe. And to ſpeak
unto you more clearly, I am an <hi>Hebrew,</hi> ſon
of that great <hi>Jacob,</hi> whoſe merit is reſpected
of all <hi>Paleſtine.</hi> My Anceſtours are illuſtrious
enough to communicate me ſome glory with
the blood which I derive from them: I ſpeak
nothing to you of my perſon, fearing to dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh
the eſteem of that which comes unto me
from thoſe famous perſons. At theſe words
<hi>Potiphar</hi> was ſeiſed with ſo ſenſible a joy, that
he could not command himſelf a longer atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
taking then the word, which he had
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:119982:69"/>
ſnatched, taken away from <hi>Joſeph,</hi> he cryed out
aloud. And what Sir, think you me inſenſible
in this point, that there ſhould need reaſons to
perſwade me to my happineſſe, and my Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters?
I look not upon your preſent fortune, nor
the glory of your Anceſtors. I not only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,
but I deſire with all my heart the honour
of your allyance. Your vertue is worth more
then your fortune. Your merit weighs more in
my ſpirit, then that of your Fathers; laying
aſide all that which is out of you, I deſire ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
nothing but you. I cheriſh a thouſand
times more your perfections, then your trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures,
and the ornaments of your ſoul, then
thoſe of your body. God is my witneſſe, that
if I had been bold enough to deſire great
things, that I ſhould not have had courage e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough
to look upon the good which you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
me. <hi>Aſſeneth</hi> is too happy, in that you have
vouchſafed to abaſe your eyes on her, all her
race will publiſh for ever your goodneſſe, and I,
my good fortune. From this time forward I
deſire that you be maſter of my fortune, that
you diſpoſe of my eſtate, and that my Daughter
reſigne a half of her heart unto you, having
no other will but yours. Notwithſtanuing Sir,
I would not that you ſhould doubt of my ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity,
if any vain ſuperſtition ſhould obſtinate
her to reject her good. The ſpirit of women
being not ſometimes capable of reaſon, is ſo
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:119982:70"/>
neither of change, though one may ſay, that
their ſex makes the greateſt part of the Worlds
inconſtancy. Their imagination is ſometimes
an eternal Law, and their reſolution a decree,
which hath the ſame neceſſities with deſtiny. I
fear that <hi>Aſeneth</hi> may be a little opinionate
upon a certain promiſe, which obliges her
(ſaith ſhe) to live alwayes a Virgin, if ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
me, this ſcruple ſhall not exerciſe much
her ſpirit; for beſides that, the chief law of
Children is to obey their Parents, by right of
nature; I will make her free of that obligation,
by the power which I hold to conſerve, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe
that of our Gods.</p>
            <p>This good Father knew not that his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
will had already conſented to the allyance
of <hi>Joſeph;</hi> for as ſoon as ſhe ſaw him, ſhe found
her affection engaged. So many charms ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared
not without making this precious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt:
there are clandeſtine mariages of the
heart as well as of the body, and often times it
happeneth, that without conſidering a perſon
with attention, one loves by deſtiny. That vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage
which was but one and twenty years old,
preſented an object too raviſhing to this young
Lady, not to raviſh all her ſoul, ſo many at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractions
gave her rather a neceſſity then an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination
to the love of his perſon. Yet muſt ſhe
make the ſhowes and difficulties, which are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary
in theſe encounters, where the women
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:119982:70"/>
endeavour only to hide their deſire, and not to
extinguiſh it. When her Father ſpake unto her
of this ſuit, an honeſt bluſh covered her cheeks,
and as he preſſed her to give conſent thereunto,
her plaints witneſſed that it was but with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gret
that ſhe obeyed <hi>Potiphar.</hi> Poor girle, how
confounded would you be, if your tears inſtead
of diſſembling you ſhould betray you? why
would you that one ſhould force from your
mouth what you give ſo willingly from the
bottom of your heart? it is ordinary with this
ſex to teach even the eyes to lie, and to give
Hypocriſie to the ſimpleſt countenances.</p>
            <p>Our Vice-Roy knew too well theſe little
policies, to be put off with that affected cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:
on the contrary, as he found her one day
a part, after having prayſed her modeſty, he
declared unto her, without any artiſice the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
of his intentions, and leaving all the fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh
complements of love unto thoſe, who have
nothing better, he aſſured her, that her allyance
was in truth the moſt ardent of his deſires, but
yet that he knew ſo well to moderate his affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
that ſhe ſhould not be conſtrained to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
him any complayſance to the prejudice of
the reverence of her Religion, and therefore if
ſhe were loath to quitt hers, that he would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour
to change his love into reſpect. But I
cannot perſwade my ſelf (added he) that the
feare to diſpleaſe a ſtatue of braſſe, or one of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:119982:71"/>
wood, ſhould obliege you to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt
of my affection. Your Gods have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
good but their matter, and if the Artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer
who created them, had made them of dirt,
their Majeſty would be as adorable, as their
ſtuffe would be precious. It is true, that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
well deceive my ſelf in the opinion of your
belief, and that ſuch a wit as yours ſhould ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
it ſelf to be ſurprized in the worſhip
of thoſe Divinities, who have filled Heaven
with nothing but thefts and adulteries. I ſpeak
not of <hi>Venus,</hi> whoſe impurities are adored, nor
of your <hi>Apis,</hi> who cannot render his Oracles
without bellowing, ſince he is an Oxe. That
<hi>Diana</hi> whom you ſerve, is ſhe not an incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
in the Heaven, a courſer in the Woods,
and a fury in hell? I would not believe that
you ſhould think the onyons and leeks which
are eaten by the hoggs, nor the Crocodiles
which devoure men, ſhould be Gods, ſince the
impuiſſance of the firſt cannot conſerve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
nor the cruelty of the other do good. Is
it not true, Madam, that you have long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned
theſe falſe Divinities, without having
yet happineſs enough to acknowledge the true.
Behold the time wherein you may be devout
without Idolatry, and adore God, without of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending
him; it is principally that which I
ſeek, aſſuring you that I deſire not ſo much to
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:119982:71"/>
be your Husband, as to give you our great God
for bridegroom.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aſseneth</hi> having thanked <hi>Joſeph</hi> for the zeale
which he witneſſed to have of her ſalvation,
received the offers of ſervice which he made
her; and to prove unto him that his Religion
pleaſed her as much as his allyance, ſhe made a
ſacrifice to the true God of all the Idols which
ſhe adored.</p>
            <p>If I were in a humor to write of viſions;
<hi>Vincent de Beauvais</hi> would ſhew you one in his
mirrour, where you might admire the provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
of God in the inſtruction of his Elect;
let thoſe who deſire it, ſeek it; for my part, I
have too many aſſured truths, to hazard my ſelf
in publiſhing dreams. Never was <hi>Potiphar</hi> more
content then to underſtand the ſucceſs of his
gueſt, who had gained a ſoul unto God, when
it was thought he endeavored only to gain a
body to his paſſion. If he would have anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
his deſire, this mariage which was to be
concluded, ſhould have been conſummate; but
<hi>Joſeph</hi> judged prud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntly, that it ought not to
be done without the conſent of the King. Being
then returned to <hi>Memphis,</hi> he beſought him to
approve his ſuit. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> who deſired but to
tie <hi>Joſeph</hi> to his State, liked this deſign, and to
haſten the execution thereof, he diſpatched a
Courtier to <hi>Heliopolis,</hi> who carried order to
<hi>Potiphar</hi> and his Daughter, to render them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:119982:72"/>
readily to the Court. I will not ſtop at
the entertainment which the King gave them,
nor likewiſe at all the magnificences which ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eoured
this nuptiall. Every one may ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently
imagine, that they were not mean, ſeeing
a puiſſant Monark was at the coſt, his favourite
the ſubject thereof. And then I remember, that
ſrom the entrance of this Hiſtory, I never pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed
to my ſelf to ſpeak of the greatneſſe of
<hi>Joſeph;</hi> but in as much as it declareth this
truth, that God leaves us not to ſuffer, but for
our glory. This feaſt being made for the whole
Court, <hi>Joſeph</hi> and his wife continued the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentments
thereof as long as they lived. They
lived happy, in that they were content; nothing
troubled them, becauſe they knew to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodate
all things to their fortune. This
continual proſperity charmed not ſo the Vice-Roy,
that he thought not of his Maſters affairs,
leaving him the care to do his own. His houſe
was the ſource, from whence flowed the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
felicity; but whileſt <hi>Egypt</hi> poſſeſſed all the
delights of the earth, the reſt of the earth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came
a great ſolitude, and they began to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge
that <hi>Joſeph</hi> had propheſied. The
Famine ran over all the neighbour Provinces,
preſenting it ſelf already upon the frontiers of
this happy Empire. At laſt notwithſtanding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
reſiſtance that her reſerver made, he could
defend no longer then ſeven years this Nation,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:119982:72"/>
his wiſdom muſt yield to that providence, that
will make it deſolate. The famine entered
therein, to continue her ſpoils without ſparing
the moſt conſiderable fortunes. After having
conſumed the Corn, ſhe devoured the whole
fields, conſtraining the people of this Country
to ſell that which they poſſeſſed, to live. In ſo
much, that in few years <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſaw himſelf
Monark of a great Kingdom, and proprietory
Lord of that which he poſſeſſed before but by
homage.</p>
            <p>Let us leave <hi>Egypt</hi> a little, and paſſe we into
<hi>Canaan,</hi> as being a long time ſince we depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
thence. Perhaps we ſhall finde a corner in
<hi>Jacobs</hi> houſe, to ſecure us from that cruel who
kills without triking, and who beſiegeth not
thoſe whom ſhe will take but inwardly. I fear
ſhe hath ſome intelligence in this Family, at
leaſt I ſee not there that good chear as former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.
Every one fearing the future, becomes good
husband of the things, whereof he had been
prodigall. And the magniſicence that produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
it ſelfe outwardly, was then a virtue ſecret
and interior. Our holy Patriark willing to
prevent death, and cure an evil which could
not yet make it ſelf felt but by the apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of falling under it, commanded his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
to diſpoſe themſelves to a voyage into <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt.</hi>
Each of them conſented to do by obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
what he ſhould have been obliged to do
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:119982:73"/>
ſhortly through neceſſity. But where go theſe
ten offenders? if they ſeek their Judge, <hi>Joſeph</hi>
is in <hi>Egypt:</hi> if they will die, famine is not more
redoubtable then death. Oh ſweet providence
of God, how equitable art thou to refer unto
<hi>Joſeph</hi> the revenge, or the pardon of his inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries!
and to make thoſe proud heads bow be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
thy faithful Servant. The Saviour of <hi>Egypt</hi>
was in the Palace, when a Page advertized him
that certain ſtrangers defired to do him reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.
As he was of a humour to obliege all the
world, he entered without long ſtay into a
Hall, where he found the Children of <hi>Jabob?</hi>
who put themſelves preſently upon their knees
to adore him. Their viſage and their language
made them known without difficulty; but if
they were known, they could not take a happy
Prince for a miſerable Brother. Our <hi>Canane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi>
having declared the neceſſity, which
brought them thither, <hi>Joſeph</hi> conſidering them
as if he had obſerved ſomething of ſuſpition in
them, asked them from whence they were: to
which anſwering with much fear, they
replyed, that they came from <hi>Canaan.</hi> The
Vice-Roy making himſelf other then he was,
ſaid unto them as a man in cholar. Without
doubt you are ſpies, that come to underſtand
the ſtate of the Kingdom, to ſerve your ſelves
upon our weakneſſe, and the neceſſity, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto
you believe the famine hath reduced us;
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:119982:73"/>
but your deſign ſhall turn only to your ruine,
and then making ſign to his Guard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
that they ſhould put the traytors in
priſon. <hi>Judah</hi> who ſaw himſelf aſſoon ſeized
on, as they had command to ſeize on him,
would defend himſelf, but with the ſubmiſſion
of a low reverence, which was waited on with
this diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>My Lord, I cannot perſwade my ſelf, that a
man full of equity ſhould cunclude that a ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition
renders us criminalls: being juſt as you
are, we hope to appear innocent as we are. If
you can take us in a lie, we will confeſſe the
treaſon, of which we are accuſed, and we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
to ſuffer the puniſhment which it ſhall
pleaſe your Excellence to ordain us. We feare
not your torments, becauſe we know your ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice;
we are of <hi>Chananée,</hi> Sonnes of one Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
who lives at home with our youngeſt
Brother. We had another Brother, but misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune
having made him fall into the paws of a
ſavage beaſt, hath raviſhed him from us. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity
hath conſtrained us to ſeek wherewith
to live, in this Country, where all things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound
by your wiſdom. Behold all the arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice
of our deſign; if you diſcover any other
ſecret, we are in your power. Truly you had
(replyed the ViceRoy) true reaſon to believe me
very ſimple, ſhould I eſteem you innocent upon
your own depoſition: where ſhall one find the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:119982:74"/>
guilty, if it be enough to deny the crimes? and
who ſhall be innocent (replyed <hi>Iudas</hi>) if to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe
be ſufficient to convict. There needs not ſo
many words (anſwered <hi>Ioſeph</hi>) the effects will
witneſſe better the truth of what you ſay, then
all your Proteſtations. One of you ſhall return
unto <hi>Canaan,</hi> and bring hither your youngeſt
Brother, whom you aſſure liveth there: if he
come, I will believe you without crime: if
you fail to bring him, I ſweare by the ſafety of
my Prince, you are ſpies. As <hi>Ioſeph</hi> had ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
this with a tone of voice ſomewhat moved,
he commanded that they ſhould be caſt into
priſon, where they ſhould remain three dayes;
but as he had a heart all full of tenderneſſe, he
had not courage enough to keep them there
longer; chuſing rather that his ſweetneſſe
ſhould puniſh them lightly, then to permit his
juſtice to treat them according to all the right
that it had to be ſevere. And then the fear
which he had that <hi>Iacob</hi> might need ſomething
in the mean time, made him reſolve to ſend
them away. Having cauſed them to come forth
out of priſon, he ſpake to them in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
            <p>Though you ſee me habited like an Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
I am not, thanks unto God, of their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
I know the Gods of <hi>Egypt,</hi> but I love the
God of <hi>Canaan:</hi> the fear of thoſe never gave
me liberty to offend this. Since you make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:119982:74"/>
to honour him, I will witneſſe unto you
the feare that I have to offend him, I promiſe
that you may all return home to your Father,
excepting him; (pointing unto <hi>Simeon</hi> in ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
theſe words) he ſhall ſerve as caution for
your return; behold the only means to make
me believe that you are true. O God how an
affliction fitly ſent hath power to bring men un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
reaſon! thoſe who could not repent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
of their cruelty in three and twenty yeers
of proſperity, began to open their eyes, and to
acknowledge that their preſent miſery was a
puniſhment of their paſſed fault. It is reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
(cryed out <hi>Reuben</hi>) that we ſuffer at this
time juſtly what we have formerly made our
Brother ſuffer without juſtice. I told you often,
that his blood would make us bluſh, and that
Heaven would not pardon us a ſin which na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
forbad us: if you had had then pitty of
<hi>Joſeph,</hi> God would have had ſome now of our
affliction; but it is no time now to be wiſe,
Heaven is not ſatisfied alwayes with repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
it will ſometimes that the puniſhment
follow the crime. All that we can do to ſuffer
profitably, is to ſuffer with patience, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
murmure. <hi>Reuben</hi> would have ſaid more,
becauſe he thought not to be underſtood by
him, who ſpake not to them but by an interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;
but <hi>Joſeph</hi> not able to ſee their teares
without mourning, retired himſelf a little
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:119982:75"/>
from their preſence, to give that liberty to his
eyes. In the mean time he cauſed their ſacks to
be filled with the beſt wheat of his Granaries,
and ſent them away, keeping him whom he
had deſigned, and cauſing him to be loaden
with Irons in the fight of his Brothers, to the
end, that the feare of his death might obliege
them to bring him <hi>Benjamin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some one may curiouſly demand why <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi>
witneſſed more ſeverity unto <hi>Simeon,</hi> then
to his other Brothers? the reſponſe is not diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult,
ſince it was reaſonable that the moſt cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal
ſhould be the moſt puniſhed, and that he
who had ſaid theſe words (behold our dream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er)
ſhould digeſt at leaſure the malice thereof.
We muſt not think nevertheleſſe, that his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
was accompanied with its ordinary incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities.
Since <hi>Simeon</hi> could aſſure with truth,
that he had never been more happy, then when
he was to be miſerable.</p>
            <p>Let us follow a little our Pilgrims, and take
up their entertainment; all their diſcourſes
were of <hi>Joſephs</hi> death, admiring that the juſtice
of God made uſe of the famine to diſcover and
puniſh their ſin. As they were arrived at the
firſt Inne, and that <hi>Zabulon</hi> had opened his ſack
to provender their Aſſes, he was very much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhed
to ſee in the mouth thereof, the ſame
peeces of gold which he had given for the price
of this wheat. His Brothers ſurprized with like
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:119982:75"/>
aſtoniſhment as he, began to feare that there
might be deceit in this liberality, and that the
Kings Servants had put this money into their
ſacks, to render them guilty. Notwithſtanding
their conſolation was in their innocence, and
all their confidence in God, who without
doubt would not permit that the malice of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other
ſhould be puniſhed in their Perſons. Put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
themſelves then into the hands of him, who
lets no body fall, they continued their way with
ſo much diligence, that they arrived in <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bron</hi>
before they were expected. <hi>Jacob</hi> was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely
glad to ſee them in full health; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
when he perceived that <hi>Simeon</hi>
was not with them, fear ſeized this poor old
man with ſo much exceſs, that there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
but his ſilence that could expreſs it. But
if the abſence of <hi>Simeon</hi> made him fear, one
might ſay that the deſign to conduct <hi>Benjamin</hi>
into <hi>Egypt</hi> would make him die. What (cryed
out this good Patriark) will you bury me alive,
and take from me a good which nature gives
me almoſt againſt my deſire? ſuffer me to live,
may be you intend to ſee me languiſh the reſt
of my dayes! I have one only Sonne that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolates
the loſs of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> and of his poor Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
and muſt I looſe him! Oh my God, how
happy had my condition been to have had no
Children, or to have had ſome more fortunate!
<hi>I</hi> had had then but my misfortunes to bewaile,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:119982:76"/>
whereas now I ſee me obliged to take the beſt
part of thoſe that afflict them. <hi>Joſeph</hi> hath ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied
the cruel hunger of a ſavage Beaſt, and
his Brother, to appeaſe ours, muſt be expoſed
to the deſire of a Barbarian, who, perchance,
will take pleaſure to torment me in the perſon
of <hi>Benjamin.</hi> What know I if he obliged not
all my Children to preſent themſelves to him,
to invelop them under one and the ſame ruine,
and to extinguiſh the name of <hi>Iſrael</hi> upon the
earth? <hi>Reuben</hi> ſeeing the ſorrowful plants of
his Father, replyed to him, my dear Father, the
ſubject which you take to afflict you, ſeems
not to me juſt enough to abandon you in this
manner, ſince it is only ſupported the vain
apprehenſions which your affection forms you.
This Vice-Roy whom you repreſent as a ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant,
hath nothing ſavage in his nature: his
courteſie would be capable to take from you
all your fears, if you knew it. And then what
likelihood, that he whom <hi>Egypt</hi> adores as their
Saviour, ſhould take pleaſure to deſtroy
eleven wretches, whoſe death can give him no
aſſurance, nor their life ſuſpition: for my part,
I would rather hope the effects of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
then go to prevent the evils which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps
will never come unto us from his rigour.
Have we not already a teſtimony of his genero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity,
in that he hath ſent us back with his bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits,
and our money?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:119982:76"/>
Alas, how weak is your diſcourſe (replyed
<hi>Jacob</hi>) that which you call benefit, is that
which I name an Artifice. Are you ſo young,
that you know not that it is ordinary with
traytors to flatter, when they will hurt; and to
give fair words, when they have evil thoughts.
If you had obſerved curiouſly the cuſtoms of
<hi>Egypt,</hi> you would have ſeen that they load the
victimes with flowers, and that the Crown
which adorns them, is the preſage of the death
which threatens them. Speak no more to me of
your deſign, if you deſire that <hi>I</hi> live. What
then my Father (ſaid <hi>Reuben</hi>) would you ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
expoſe ten of your Children to a certain
death then to tempt a hazard, which may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily
ſucceed? <hi>Simeon</hi> is ingaged upon our faith;
we will never ſuffer that the ſubject of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence
be the cauſe of his ruine: if the peril
be evident, we deſire that it be common. <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jamin</hi>
who had heard this diſcourſe, beſought
his Father to permit him to render that proof
of his love to his Brothers. That if he ſhould
die with them, he ſhould have this conſolation,
to have had Children ſo ſtreightly united in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,
that death which divides all, could not
have power to ſeparate them. Every one liked
this thought, and prayſed his reſolution; there
was none but <hi>Jacob,</hi> who witneſſed by his tears,
and his ſighs, that he conſented not thereunto
but with conſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>int. <hi>Reuben</hi> who ſuffered not
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:119982:77"/>
without pain the ſorrow of his Father, and
who reſented all his griefs, proteſted to him,
that in caſe any evil ſhould happen unto <hi>Benja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min,</hi>
he would give him leave to ſlay his two
Sonnes. <hi>Judas</hi> made almoſt the ſame proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
that his eldeſt did, adding that he would
render himſelf pledge for him life for life. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
this long conteſtation, as they emptyed the
ſacks for the ſecond voyage, every one was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhed
to finde there his money, but there
was not one who gave not the glory of this
benefit to the liberality of the <hi>Vice-Roy,</hi> to the
end, that <hi>Jacob</hi> might conceive good hopes by
this univerſal applauſe. Behold th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n this good
Patriark, who embraced his Children with ſo
much tenderneſs and tears, as if he had been
condemned to ſee them no more. Above all,
taking leave of <hi>Benjamin,</hi> one would have
thought that he ſaid adieu to all his content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;
notwithſtanding the diſpleaſure of this
departure, hindered him not to think upon the
neceſſities of this voyage, and to command his
Sonnes whatſoever prudence could give them
of good advice.</p>
            <p>My Children (ſaid he to them) if my life be
yet conſiderable to you, I conjure you to have
care of yours; ſince the ſame accidents which
touch you, paſſe even to my heart; indeavour
to avoid them with diſcretion. Truſt not ſo
much to the ſweetneſſe of that Prince, whoſe
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:119982:77"/>
goodneſs you prayſe unto me, that you ſhould
not feare to provoke him. The affection of the
great ones of the earth is ſo delicate, that very
often there needs but a touch to break it. The
words that we ſay unto them ſhould be of ſilk
to pleaſe; which is found true in all perſons of
condition; but principally in regard of thoſe
whom fortune hath elevated. They fear ſo
much contempt, that they ſeek adoration, as
if their greatneſſe appeareth not, but by the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion
of the leſſer. Let your demands be
humble, and your anſwers modeſt. Whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
ſhall become of your life, make no uſe of a
lie, to make you appear true; becauſe this
monſter is known alwayes by ſome place, and
though he preſents a pleaſing viſage, his lower
parts are deformed: how fair ſoever a Devil
be when he ſhews himſelf, he hath alwayes the
tail or foot of a Beaſt. But though that vertue
may ſteed you more with this Prince then any
other thing, fail not to offer him of my part
this little of our beſt mirrhe, of our Theriack,
and of all that which you ſhall judge to be rare
in <hi>Egypt.</hi> Preſents diſpoſe the hearts of thoſe
whom we deſire favours; if we fear their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,
they tie their hands, and ſtop the evil ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects
of their power. I am of opinion, that you
ſhould take twice as much money as is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
for your employment: you know not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
they did not tempt your fidelity, when
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:119982:78"/>
they put into your ſacks the ſame peeces of
gold which you brought. Rendering them
freely, it will be a teſtimony of your honeſty,
and perhaps an effect of juſtice. Behold my
dear Children, the laſt words of y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur poor Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
if your prudence conduct not this voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age
with ſo much diſcretion, that the good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe
may prolong my pilgrimage upon
earth.</p>
            <p>After this long diſcourſe, and many tears ſhed
of one part and the other, all the Brothers took
their way towards <hi>Egypt,</hi> where they arrived
after much pains. When they entered into the
Palace, <hi>Joſeph</hi> was by chance at a window, from
whence he perceived them. As he knew <hi>Benja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min</hi>
amongſt the reſt, he commanded the Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard
of the houſe to get the dinner ready, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
he would eat with them. In the mean
time, he conducted our Pilgrims into a great
Hall: but having conceived ſome fear before
they entered, they declared unto him, that they
had brought the money which they had found
in opening their ſacks: Upon which the Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard
having aſſured them, to make their joy
compleat, he brought them <hi>Simeon.</hi> I leave the
careſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of this interview, and the Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
which were made reciprocally. The feaſt
being ready, <hi>Joſeph</hi> appeared and received their
preſents with much teſtimony of good will. As
he had entertained them, he asked them if
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:119982:78"/>
their Father lived yet, and if that young man
was their youngeſt Brother; <hi>Judas</hi> having an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered
yes, that good Prince fixing his eyes
upon <hi>Benjamin,</hi> felt himſelf preſſed to the
heart ſo tenderly, that he retired into his Cabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net
to hide there his tears. After the courſe of
them was ſtopped, he came to them again to
waſh. They had layed a Table for the Vice-Roy,
and for his Wife, who knew all the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.
Another for the ſtrangers, and the third for
ſome <hi>Egyptian</hi> Lords, who could not ſee their
gods, to be eaten without indignation. This
ceremony was accompanied with two circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances,
which gave much matter of thought
to our <hi>Cananeans.</hi> The firſt was, as St. <hi>Ephraim</hi>
reports, that <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſtriking with a Rod upon
his Cup, commanded that <hi>Reuben</hi> ſhould take
the chief place, according to the right of ſenio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity;
and then ſtriking eleven times, he named
the others, and cauſed them to be ſeated accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
to the order of their birth. If this firſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident
ſurprized the ſpirit of the ſtrangers, the
ſecond merited no leſſe admiration. After that
all the meat was ſerved, <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſent by an Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
a plate of his ſervice to each of his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
and when it came to <hi>Benjamins</hi> turn, he
cauſed him to carry him five. This proceeding
gave aſtoniſhment to them all, notwithſtanding
no body darred to demand the cauſe thereof.
This good cheer made them forget the deſign
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:119982:79"/>
of their voyage, but the Vice-Roy had given
order that their ſacks ſhould be filled. The next
day, being up betimes in the morning, they
took leave of their benefactor with words,
which witneſſed enough, that they were not
ingrateful. As they were a quarter of a mile
from the Town, <hi>Benjamin</hi> who travelled laſt,
heard a noiſe like the trampling of horſes, of
which he had not almoſt advertized his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
but they ſaw a little after ten or twelve
Horſmen, who with ſwords in their hands came
upon them in full careere: the confuſion of
their cry gave them as much fear, as the ſhining
of their ſemiters; notwithſtanding their inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence
aſſured them in ſome manner, until that
the Captain cryed unto them to ſtay.</p>
            <p>To underſtand their fear, it was requiſite to
ſee their viſage, where it was painted, and to
conſider how one ſole word rendered them
immoveable. Truly Sirs, ſaid the Steward of
the houſe, behold ſuch an acknowledgement as
I never heard; to ſteal the goods of another,
after having received from him all kind of
courteſies, is to pay benefits in a new faſhion!
were you not content to carry away the ſort of
<hi>Egypt,</hi> but you muſt ſteal the Cup of my Lord?
theſe words ſurprized ſo their ſpirits, that no
body could anſwer except <hi>Benjamin,</hi> who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed
unto them with a modeſty which mark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
enough his vertue. What probability is there
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:119982:79"/>
that we ſhould be culpable of this crime, after
having brought back again from the further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
parts of <hi>Canaan,</hi> the money which we
might have kept without ſuſpition and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
fear. His Brothers taking the word, cryed
out with thouſand Proteſtations of their inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence,
that they conſented that he who had
done this robbery, ſhould be condemned to
death. They took them at their words, and
preſently made ſearch for the offender, viſiting
the ſacks in order, even till they had opened
<hi>Benjamins</hi> ſack, where the Cup and ſilver
Voider was found. It were neceſſary to ſee a
malefactor when his witneſſes have convicted
him, ſo that he can ſpeak no more for himſelf,
to comprehend the apprehenſion of <hi>Jacobs</hi>
Children. <hi>Benjamin</hi> ſeemed to be the moſt cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable,
and the <hi>Egyptians</hi> made ſhew to deſire
none but him: yet his Brothers followed him,
rather to revile him with injuries, then to ſerve
him in this occaſion. One blamed his artifice,
another taking his out-rages farther off, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached
him that he held this vice of his
race, and that he might well take away the
Cup of their benefactor, ſince his Mother had
likewiſe ſtolen away the Gods of her Father;
and that the ambition of <hi>Joſeph</hi> would have
raviſhed the right of the legitimates. From
words they would have come to blowes, if the
Steward had not ſaid unto them, that the
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:119982:80"/>
judgement of that affaire appertained not unto
them.</p>
            <p>Who can expreſſe their confuſion, when the
preſence of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> conſtrained them to abaſe
their fight? never were they more aſhamed,
and never ſeemed <hi>Ioſeph</hi> more offended. As
ſoon as he ſaw them, he ſaid unto them with an
accent full of ſharpneſſe: is it thus then that
you acknowledge the benefits, wherewith you
are obliged unto me? knew you no honeſter
means to requite me? ſince it is not in your
power to be good, you ſhould addreſſe your
ſelves to ſome other then to him, who better
then any man of the world knows the ſecret
thoughts of men: have I not ſufficiently made
appear unto you, that I am not ignorant in the
art of divination? <hi>Iudas</hi> taking the word re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed
to him modeſtly, It wonld be to adde
impudence to our misfortune, if we ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
to excuſe him: notwithſtanding, though
we be more unfortunate then culpable, we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
all to our condemnation. Your favours had
too much obliged us to ſerve you: let us die
ſince we have done the contrary: that ſhall be,
if it pleaſe your Highneſſe the puniſhment of
your ſlaves. The Vice-Roy interrupting his
diſcourſe, and faining to put himſelf in choler,
ſaid unto him. What have you obſerved any
thing in me, from whence you might judge me
capable of injuſtice? I know as well to
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:119982:80"/>
make the difference of the Innocents, as to pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh
the offenders. Return all into your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie,
and let him, who is convicted of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order
remain my ſlave. It is not reaſonable to
ordain a general puniſhment to a particular
fault; why ſhould you undergoe the pain of a
theft which you have not ſo much as known?
<hi>Iudas</hi> who apprehended death leſſe then this
ſentence, approaching <hi>Ioſeph</hi> with much humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
repreſented to him that his poor Father li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
not but with the ſoul of this young man,
he would die as ſoon as he ſhould believe him
dead. That he was engaged to bring him back
again unto <hi>Canaan;</hi> at laſt he concluded with
theſe ardent words. It is by the tears of this
feeble old man, that I conjure you to permit the
return of <hi>Benjamin.</hi> But if your juſtice will
make an example to the wicked, I offer my ſelf
willingly to ſuffer the puniſhment of his ſinne,
loving better to lead a miſerable life in Irons,
then to ſee my Father languiſh the remainder of
his dayes. At the ſame time <hi>Benjamin</hi> caſt
himſelf at his feet, and ſhewed himſelf more
eloquent with his eys then with his mouth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
he ſhed more tears then he uttered
words.</p>
            <p>But is not this diſſimulation enough, will
he jeſt longer? no, <hi>Joſeph</hi> could no more, his
eyes were full of tears, and his heart with ſighs.
This good Prince not longer able to command
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:119982:81"/>
his joy, made ſign with his hand to his people
to depart, and then breaking out into ſighs,
which love and grief hindered to be intelligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
he ſaid unto them the beſt that he could. I
am your Brother <hi>Joſeph,</hi> doth our Father live
yet? as ſoon as he returned to the liberty of
ſpeech, his Brothers loſt it, for fear ſent back
into their ſpirit, all that which their wit had
invented to the ruine of their preſerver. <hi>Joſeph</hi>
perceived it, and to diſſipate their apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
he uſed the ſweeteſt and moſt gracious
words that his goodneſs could pronounce.
Fear not my Brothers, I am <hi>Joſeph,</hi> yes my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
I am that <hi>Joſeph</hi> whom you ſold to the
<hi>Iſmaelites.</hi> Perhaps you are troubled, or afraid
to believe it; you might have cauſe for it, if
proſperity could change me, and your conduct
accuſe you. I am your Brother, and you are the
Authours of my good fortune<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> It is the provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
of God, that hath conducted me into
<hi>Egypt</hi> for your comfort, ſince you have been the
cauſe of my glory, my power ſhall not be the
motive of your fear. I have wherewith to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite
you; without you I had never been the
Maſter of <hi>Egypt.</hi> I rather look upon the deſign
of Heaven, then the intention of your malice;
fix your thoughts rather on my love then on
your hate: conſider leſſe my arm then my
heart. I am <hi>Joſeph</hi> your Brother. But leſt there
ſhould arrive any inconvenience to our good
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:119982:81"/>
Father, return ſpeedily to him, and aſſure him
that his Sonne lives, and that he lives for the
conſolation and ſuccour of all his. As he had
ended, this amiable Brother caſt himſelf on
<hi>Benjamins</hi> neck, mingling his tears with his,
which he did to all the others, kiſſing them
with much love and tenderneſs. All this paſſed
not ſo ſecretly, but the Court and <hi>Pharaoh</hi> had
knowledge thereof. The King extremely joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
to have a new means to oblige his Miniſter,
commanded that thoſe ſtrangers ſhould be
brought to his Palace, where they were treated
magnificently. Nothing was ſpared to render
them fitly unto <hi>Jacob,</hi> which they had order to
carry to him, to the end, to receive the honours
which his age and quality merited.</p>
            <p>Who can conceive the thoughts of that good
Patriark, when his Children aſſured him, that
his much beloved <hi>Joſeph</hi> lived, and beſides that
he raigned in <hi>Egypt.</hi> Surely the Scripture ſaith,
that it happened unto him, as unto thoſe who
have fair dreams. During their ſleep, they ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine
that they are Kings, that they poſſeſs
Mountains of gold, that all the delights of the
world come to cheriſh them; and in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
they ſee their Caſtles, their Scepters and
their Crowns vaniſh with the ſhadows of the
night, leaving them only the pleaſure to have
been ſweetly deceived. This compariſon ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth
not ill the cogitations of this reverend
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:119982:82"/>
old man, who could not take the true Hiſtory
of his dear Sonne but for a fair dream, and a
pleaſing illuſion. But who cannot but accuſe
<hi>Joſeph</hi> of hardneſſe, to have ſo long time lived
in delights, without thinking on the misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes
of his poor Father? who condemns his
Conduct, blames the providence of God, who
would hide the greatneſſe of this Patriark, to
make it ſhine forth with more glory. May be
he permitteth alſo that the little wiſdom of
men intervene in this affaire, to the end, to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie
the merit of the one and the other, by a
patience of three and twenty yeers.</p>
            <p>Whileſt we permit our ſpirit to ſound the
counſels of heaven, <hi>Jacob</hi> arrived at <hi>Thebes,</hi>
which began to be the Town of the <hi>Heroes,</hi>
ſince it lodged ſo great a man, ſcarce was he
entered therein, but he commanded <hi>Judas</hi> to go
to the Court, to advertiſe <hi>Joſeph</hi> of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.
It was no ſooner ſignified unto him, but
he departed, and came to <hi>Goſhen</hi> with all his
Family. The inability to expreſs the joy which
<hi>Jacob</hi> received from the life and fortune of his
Sonne, diſpenſes me to ſpeak of their firſt inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view.
Their extaſie was ſo ſweet, that it raviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
me my ſelf, and permits me not the liberty
to admire it. I cannot notwithſtanding but
wonder that this paſſion, which hath often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
killed thoſe whom grief could not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come,
had not deſtroyed an old man, who was
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:119982:82"/>
more feeble, and loved more then many others,
who have witneſſed their extreme content by
their ſudden death. Sometimes this good Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
was ſeen hanging on the neck of <hi>Joſeph,</hi>
now he embraced his Daughter in Law: and
then as if the careſſes and kindneſſes were all to
the Children, he kiſſed amorouſly <hi>Ephraim,</hi>
and <hi>Manaſses.</hi> The affection of the one and
the other being in ſome faſhion ſatisfied, <hi>Ioſeph</hi>
thought it fit to viſit <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> before his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents
ſhould preſent themſelves at the Court.
As he ſeparated himſelf from them, he coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelled
them, if the King ſhould offer them any
aboad, to chuſe no other but <hi>Goſhen.</hi> Two
Reaſons made this advice to be approved, the
one, becauſe it was the richeſt Country of the
Kingdom: the ſecond, that they ſhould be
withdrawn from the Court, where proſperities
being alwayes envied, theirs ſhould not be
without jealouſie: beſides, that the <hi>Egyptians</hi>
had in horror that kinde of life, of which <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi>
and his Children made profeſſion. This
Counſel approved, the Vice-Roy returning to
<hi>Memphis,</hi> gave <hi>Jacob</hi> leyſure to taſte his good
fortune, &amp; to admire the ſweet providence of
God, who is pleaſed to do miracles, to comfort
his faithful Servants.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pharaoh</hi> having underſtood that the Father
of his favorite, was at <hi>Goſhen,</hi> commanded
that they ſhould haſte his voyage: being in his
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:119982:83"/>
preſence, this Prince who was full of goodneſs,
gave him all the entertainment with which he
ſuppoſed to be able to oblige him. Above all
the honour which he rendered him, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
which he ſhewed him was remarkable:
never entered he into his Chamber, but he
went to receive him at the door, and if he ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
there any time, his ſeat and that of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty
had nothing that could ſeparate them. To
ſpeak truth, this civility ſhewed much good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination
in the diſpoſition of <hi>Pharaoh:</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
we muſt confes, that he did not get
all the honour which was due to this reverend
old man. The day that <hi>Jacob</hi> was to depart to
retire himſelf unto <hi>Rameſes,</hi> a City in the Land
of <hi>Goſhen,</hi> the King admiring the vigour of
this body, which had already ſuffered the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
of more then an age, and indured the vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
of a thouſand incommodities, asked him
what age he was, to which this good Patriark
anſwered, that it was a hundred and thirty
yeers ſince <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſaw the world; but that his age
was not almoſt but the infancy of his Anceſtors:
upon this anſwer he took leave of the King,
with the acknowledgements which ſo many
courteſies required. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> who knew as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly
the ſanctity of <hi>Jacob,</hi> as he reſpected his
merit, would not let him depart from him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
he had received his benediction, making
more accompt of the good wiſhes of this wiſe
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:119982:83"/>
old man, then of all the favours that he had
done him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joſeph</hi> having conducted <hi>Jacob</hi> into <hi>Goſhen,</hi>
gave his Maſter much admiration, when he
asked him what colour he would have his
ſheep; becauſe that his Father who had the
care of them, knew a ſecret to cloath them in
his livery. If this propoſition ſurprized <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh,</hi>
the experience which he had thereof
ſhould give no leſſe aſtoniſhment. It was then
in the innocence of the Country, and amongſt
the Lambs that <hi>Iacob</hi> lived ſeventeen yeers, the
moſt contented and happy life that could be
deſired; but at laſt God would recompence ſo
many travels, the merit whereof he already
poſſeſſed: having made him underſtand his
will, he ſoon gave advertiſement thereof unto
<hi>Ioſeph,</hi> who haſted unto <hi>Goſhen</hi> with all his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily.
It is not my deſign to touch all the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances
of this death, but to report only
that which concerns the glory of <hi>Egypts</hi> preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.
Two dayes before he rendered his ſoul,
he called his dear Sonne, and after having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended
to him his other Children, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared
to him, that God would for the glory
of his name, that he ſhould be the chief of two
Tribes, in the perſon of his Children, and that
to render them worthy of this favour, he deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
to bleſſe them. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> having made them
to come, and placed <hi>Manaſses</hi> at the right
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:119982:84"/>
hand of his Father, and <hi>Ephraim</hi> at the left,
according to the order of their birth, our good
old man croſſing his arms, changed his right
hand upon the youngeſt, and layd his left hand
upon the eldeſt. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was aſtoniſhed at this
change, untill that <hi>Iacob</hi> had made him under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
a myſtery, of which the ſecret imports,
that all our benedictions ſhould come unto us
from the Croſſe.</p>
            <p>It would be very hard to expreſs the reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
which all <hi>Egypt</hi> had of this death. The
King commanded that they ſhould mourn for
him threeſcore and ten dayes, during which,
even the Ladies of the Court were ſeen to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect
their hair, and inſtead of charms and fucus
to cover their faces with dirt. The <hi>Perſians</hi>
burn not the dead, becauſe they fear to do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury
to that god which they adore, to feed
him with fleſh. For a contrary reaſon the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians</hi>
embalm theirs, thinking it would be
to prophane the bodies, to cauſe them to be
devoured of that Element, which they take for
a wild beaſt. The body of <hi>Iacob</hi> was buried
according to the cuſtom of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and then he
was tranſported into <hi>Hebron,</hi> by the expreſs
commandment which he left in dying. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heſe
funeral honours were rendered to <hi>Iacob;</hi> but
in conſideration of his Sonne, whom in having
merit enough for all his, gained them the love
and reverence of a whole Nation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:119982:84"/>
I would underſtand now of theſe petty men,
who know nothing but what they feel, and who
deny a providence, becauſe they cannot touch
it with their hand, if God deſpiſeth thoſe
whom he afflicts, and if our traverſes or croſſes
be a proof of his hate. It is true, they can
ſhew a <hi>Ioſeph</hi> obedient, and hated in his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
houſe; patient and deſpiſed in perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;
faithful and envied in his ſervitude; chaſt
and ſuſpected in his temptation; innocent and
afflicted in a priſon. But we ſhould not ſo fix
our eyes upon his miſery, that we ſhould not
raiſe them to admire his glory, if it be not that
we cannot endure the ſplendor thereof, or that
his greatneſs hath too much elevation to be
perceived. Who would ever have thought
that God would have conducted <hi>Ioſeph</hi> into a
Palace, when his Brothers caſt him into a Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern?
who could perſwade himſelf, that he
would have put the Scepter into his hand, when
he tyed them with chains of Iron? it belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
but to an infinite power to do ſuch mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vells,
and to ſave men when we believe them
loſt. It is ſomething from a ſhepheard to ſee
himſelf favorite of a great Monark; it is no
ſmall matter to be the delight of a people; it
is much to be the ſavorite of the one and of the
other; but this is not yet the height of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
of our innocent Patriark, his name marks
out but augmentation, his fortune but great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:119982:85"/>
his words are received like the Oracles,
his actions reverenced like holy things; his
inclination doth the will of another; and the
obedience which they render to the Laws, is
not more exact then that which they bring to
his orders. Vertue is couragious, a recompence
which is not infinite, ſeems not reaſonable to
her; a God can pay her merit, provided that
he give himſelf, nothing but him cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
her. <hi>Joſeph</hi> poſſeſſed the favour of four
Monarks, was Regent, and ſaver of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and
Tutor of <hi>Amaſis,</hi> the one of her moſt amiable
Kings. His Father honoured him, his Brothers
adored him as their Maſter, and whole Nations
acknowledged him for the greateſt miracle of
wiſedom of his age. I know no body ſo deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate
to refuſe to ſuffer thirty yeers to raign
fourſcore. Notwithſtanding as I have ſaid, the
vertue of <hi>Joſeph</hi> had not been recompenſed, if
God had not made him Monark of an Empire,
where many Kings would be vaſſals. There
was but heaven, which had treaſures worthy
of him.</p>
            <p>I could enlarge my ſelf in many things which
arrived to <hi>Ioſeph</hi> fince his Fathers death, even
to his own; but what can one imagine more
then a perfect felicity, which accompanied
him even to the hundred and twelfth yeere of
his life? I have not docility enough to tie me
to the relations of <hi>Helinandus,</hi> nor compla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:119982:85"/>
to believe the quarrel of <hi>Benjamin,</hi> and
of <hi>Pharaoh's</hi> ſon, without ſeeking for fables,
we have truths enough, the authority which
may come to our Patriarch from a lie, renders
him not more illuſtrious.</p>
            <p>But it is time to ſpeak of his death, to come
to the higheſt point of his glory. This
great, this happy, this wiſe, this holy
Prince, having paſſed beyond an Age, went to
live in eternity, it was notwithſtanding after
he had commanded his Nation to tranſport
his bones into <hi>Paleſtine.</hi> Perhaps by a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
Providence of Heaven, to the end that he
might be of the golden number of thoſe who
ſhould partake the Reſurrection of the Saviour.
May be alſo for the fear which he had, that
thoſe, who made Gods of their chalk, and of
their calves, might come to adore him, of
whom they held ſo many benefits. He who
would make <hi>Moſes</hi> the God of <hi>Pharoah,</hi> ſuffered
that the <hi>Egyptians</hi> naturally carried unto Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie,
ſhould acknowledge after his death a
Divinitie which they had honoured during his
life.</p>
            <p>It is the opinion of many knowing men, that
<hi>Joſeph</hi> was no ſooner dead, but the <hi>Egyptians</hi>
(notwithſtanding any reſiſtance which the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi>
made) took his bodie all embalmed,
and caſt it into the <hi>Nile,</hi> to be adored there
with the other Gods, under the name of <hi>Serapis.</hi>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:119982:86"/>
The picture of this God ſeems to favour this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion,
becauſe they repreſent him under the
viſage of a young man, who carried a meaſure
of corn and bread on his head. This conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture
is yet aided by the figure of the Ox, under
which <hi>Serapis</hi> was alſo acknowledg'd, which
<hi>Moſes</hi> ſeems to inſinuate, when in <hi>Deuteronomy</hi>
he compares <hi>Joſeph</hi> to an Oxe. The Etymologie
is not contrarie to this ſenſe, whether we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive
this word <hi>Serapis</hi> from <hi>Sar,</hi> which ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies
Prince, from whence we have made our
French Sire; and from <hi>Apis,</hi> which ſignifies an
Oxe, as if one ſhould ſay the Prince of Oxen:
Or that we make it to come with <hi>Firmicus,</hi> from
<hi>Sara,</hi> and from <hi>Aſeph,</hi> or <hi>Apis,</hi> which is the
ſame by the ſmoothneſſe of a figure, which the
Greeks name <hi>Metatheſis.</hi> In this ſenſe <hi>Serapis</hi>
implies no other thing, but the Prince of the
children of <hi>Sara,</hi> an honour which is due to
<hi>Joſeph,</hi> ſince he is the firſt of the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> who
hath born the illuſtrious name of Prince.</p>
            <p>It would be eaſie to produce many other
conjectures, notwithſtanding without ſtopping
at the things which our incomparable <hi>Joſeph</hi>
hath not deſired, I will touch one very conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable
to his glory. The <hi>Egyptians</hi> having
forgotten the benefits of him who had ſaved
them, loſt likewiſe the reſpect which they owed
to his Nation; from this contempt ariſe an
hatred of their name; this hate kindled ſo
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:119982:86"/>
cruel an envy againſt their perſons, that it was
a great part of their Religion to perſecute
them. <hi>Moſes</hi> not able to ſuffer theſe outrages,
reſolved upon a flight; but he muſt have the
bones of <hi>Joſeph.</hi> What means, ſince they had
been caſt into the current of <hi>Nile,</hi> to conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate
the waters thereof. The <hi>Rabbines,</hi> who
pleaſe themſelves with Fables, make here a
ſheep to ſpeak, to inſtruct a Prophet. It ſeems
unto me more reaſonable to receive that which
others aſſure, and to ſay that <hi>Moſes</hi> knew the
place of the River, where thoſe precious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques
were, having written the great Name
in a plate of gold, which floated upon the
water, until it reſted it ſelf upon the holy bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die.</p>
            <p>Now, my Reader, think you that affliction
and calumny can hurt innocence; and that
one ſhould avoid the tempeſts which lead hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily
to the Port? From what favour can one
expect more proſperities then hatred and envy
have procured to our Patriarch, ſince the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion
of a Kingdome was but the leaſt part of
his recompence. O how much are you to be
wiſhed, ſweet misfortunes, who prick us not
but to awake us; how powerfully you attract
my deſire, precious calumnies, who caſt no ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows
on our reputation, but to make it break
forth reſplendently. But rather holy Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
of my God, how amiable art thou, ſince
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:119982:87"/>
it is thee who changeſt theſe afflictions into
joyes, and theſe calumnies into a ſolid and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limited
glory.</p>
            <p>Tell me, my dear Reader, is it not true, that
it is impoſſible for thee to read the Hiſtory of
our <hi>Joſeph,</hi> but thou ſhalt ſuffer, and thou ſhalt
triumph? It is in his perſon that innocence ſighs
with ſo good a grace, that to ſee him, and not
to ſuffer with him, to ſuffer with him without
taſting a ſecret joy, are two of thoſe things
which we judge impoſſible. I know not if it
be vertue or nature in me; but I never remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
to have contemplated the conduct of that
fortunate wretch, that my heart was not mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified,
and all my ſenſes made conformable un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
his. His brothers perſecuted me in his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon;
I deſcended with him into the Ceſtern, to
combat there the fear and horrour of the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers.
I went into <hi>Egypt</hi> in his company, and
without being expoſed to the temptation of
his Miſtreſſe, I put my ſelf willingly to his
chain, ſuffering with pleaſure the incommodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
of a priſon, where he found pains without
trouble, and gall without bitterneſſe. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe
that following the pomp and magnificence
of his triumph, my admiration was greateſt,
but that my joy was leſſe, then when I lamented
with him under the Irons, and in the chains.</p>
            <p>I expect the ſame feelings from all thoſe who
ſhall read this work, ſince I ſuppoſe ſo much
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:119982:87"/>
good nature, and more vertue in them then I
have my ſelf. No body can fix his eyes here
without drawing advantage thence, provided
that they read with attention, it ſhall not be
without profit. I dare even to promiſe my
ſelf, that the curious, who ſeek nothing but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſement,
ſhall be here happily deceived, and
that the truth of the Hiſtory ſhall have more
force to perſwade them, then the fiction of a
<hi>Romance,</hi> artifice to deceive them. Behold the
principal fruits that one may gather from
hence; there is not one perſon in this action,
who inſtructs us not, either with his words, or
with his example.</p>
            <p>The Fathers ſhall learn from <hi>Jacob</hi> to divide
their heart with ſo much equality to their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,
that their love cauſe no domeſtick war
in their Family. I know well, that it is hard
to keep ſtrictly this juſtice, and that the reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance,
and ſympathy of humour have power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
charms to ſurpriſe the parents. The beaſts
themſelves, who cannot obſerve the attracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
of nature, leave themſelves to goe after
their conduct. They ſay that the Partridge
hath moſt tenderneſſe for that of her chickens,
who toucheth immediately her heart whilſt ſhe
ſits upon them, as if the approach of that ſource
of love gave right to this preference; and
though the features of the face, nor the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
of the temper ſhould not make this inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:119982:88"/>
in the fathers and in the mothers, there
are other reaſons that ſolicit them ſometimes
to give themſelves unequally to their children.
For the moſt part the youngeſt have great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages
upon the eldeſt, whether they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
from the intereſt of the cauſe, or derive
from that of the effect. One may love them
with preference, becauſe the infirmity of their
age requireth ſuccour and care, which would
be unneceſſary and unſeemly in behalf of the
ſtrong: we ſupport not but what is delicate,
and leans. This natural ſweetneſſe which ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
them ſupple to the will of their parents, is
no weak motive of their affection. Thoſe who
diſpute their ſervices with them, make their
power to be doubted; thoſe who render them
without conſtraint, ſhew it, and confirm it.
Moreover, if it be true, that fathers live in
their children, have they not ſome reaſon to
cheriſh more the youngeſt, who promiſe
them advantage thereof, both becauſe they have
a longer file of years before them, and becauſe
they have more condeſcendencies to the cares
of their old age.</p>
            <p>I ſpeak not of innocence and vertue, ſince it
is certain that they ſhould draw the heart and
affection of the parents whereſoever they are.
But notwithſtanding any juſtice that he hath
to prefer the youngeſt before the eldeſt, or theſe
before the others, a father ſhould fly the exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:119982:88"/>
and apparent teſtimonies of his eſteem,
foraſmuch as he may provoke many, willing to
favour one alone. The marks of the affection
which they gave them, are the Butts where en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy
diſcharges her ſelf, and the ſpurs to hatred,
which perſecute them. Perhaps <hi>Joſeph</hi> had been
cheriſhed of his brothers, if he had not bin better
habited then they; at leaſt, we may underſtand
that the robe with which he was gratified, was
the chief cauſe of the jealouſie that ſold him.
Love then, Parents, love, but love equally, or if
you cannot, love ſecretly, and in ſilenee, that
your affection be as hidden as its principle.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jacob</hi> had great motives to cheriſh his <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph;</hi>
he was the Image of <hi>Rahel</hi> his dear wife,
he was that of all the vertues, which appeared
with ſo much luſtre in his viſage, that one
might know them in his perſon; and yet ſo
many juſt motives of his love, could not ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie
him, nor all his prudence moderate his
paſſion.</p>
            <p>In the brothers of <hi>Joſeph</hi> we have the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
and the figure of thoſe monſters who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
ſee a good quality in thoſe whom the birth,
or ſociety of life ſhould render commendable,
without an envious eye, or being craſed with
jealouſie. One muſt be a fool to merit their
good will, or at leaſt he muſt not be more able
then they, to avoid their hate. They will ſell
their own bloud, provided they may remove a
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:119982:89"/>
vertue that incommodates them. But certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
it happens always, that they repent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
of their cruelty, and if there be not
found a Monarch to raiſe up <hi>Joſeph,</hi> there is a
God who puniſheth them, and protects him.
For my part, I confeſſe, notwithſtanding any
trouble we ſuſtain in ſuffering ſtroaks from an
hand which ſhould defend us, that I ſhould
love better to act in ſuch like encounter, the
part of a Martyr, then the office of a Tyrant
or Executioner, for in the end rage confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth,
and patience crowneth.</p>
            <p>But what inſtruction may not one derive
from the misfortunes, and from the proſperities
of <hi>Joſeph?</hi> Firſt, my Reader, learn from him,
that it is important to hide that Sun and thoſe
Lights, which ſhew you, I would ſay that you
ſhould not publiſh the merit which you have.
Lay not forth your ſelves the fruit of your
ſheaves, becauſe that your brethren may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,
that there is aſmuch vanity in this teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony,
which you render you, as there is free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
and ſimplicity in diſcovering your ſelves.
Have a care to do well, and leave that of prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
you unto others; you ſhall loſe nothing of
your price; you have God for caution of that
which men owe you. If it happeneth that
Heaven put you into credit, abuſe it not; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
your fortune as a proof of your vertue,
and as a means that is preſented to you to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:119982:89"/>
it; if you have power, make it known by
your good deeds, and not by your revenges. I
confeſſe that there is ſome ſweetneſſe to reſent
ones ſelf of an injury, but there is glory and
merit to pardon it. Reſemble not thoſe gods
of the Ancients, unto whom they gave incenſe,
for fear they ſhould raiſe ſtorms. It is a fatal
power, that to hurt men; there are none but
the Devils that can derive glory from thence.
Contemplate our Patriarch in <hi>Pharaohs</hi>
throne, behold his traitors and his murtherers
at his feet; he had the thunder in his hand, he
made uſe thereof but to make them afraid, yet
ſeemed he to repent himſelf of that. Imitate
thoſe tears which mollified him upon the abaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
and humiliation of thoſe who had not
ſpared his bloud. I doubt not but you have
in the beginnings of this exerciſe, ſome repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
to practiſe it; but I dare aſſure, that the
endevour which you ſhall make, will produce
you the ſweetneſſe of a joy which will raviſh
you. He who revengeth himſelf, ſurmounts
not commonly but the cowardly; he who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicts
his ſenſe, triumpheth alwaies like an
honeſt man. Oh how ſweet and glorious is it
to have the thunderbolts in hand, and to make
uſe but of the thunder!</p>
            <p>But ſince we are almoſt continually to ſuffer
in this life, let us conſider our Patriarch in all
his misfortunes, and his example will tell us
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:119982:90"/>
that which we ought to do in like encounters.
Happeneth it that your brothers perſecute you,
look upon him in his ſobbing under the knife
of an inhumane, who pardoned him not, but
to abandon him to the beaſts more ſavage, then
an evil brother, if yet there be any ſuch. He
fell from their hands into the bottome of a
Ditch, he made thereof a Pulpit, from whence
he ſent a thouſand ſighs unto Heaven, to ſolicit
there the pardon of his executioners. I aſſure
you, my dear Reader, that he carried his pains
with ſo much conformity, that God took plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
therein, and that this pleaſure obliged him
to ſtir him up new troubles. You will judge
when he comes forth of his Sepulchre, that he
ſhall riſe again to the hope of a life leſſe incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious
then his; a few paces from thence, he
found chains, which ſerved notwithſtanding
but to hold him more ſtrongly to the will of
his Creator. He paſſed into <hi>Egypt,</hi> they caſt
him headlong into a priſon; did this hinder
him to adore him who brought him thither?
So far was he from it, that he ſeemed to ſee
him and to hear him, as he had raiſed him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove
the <hi>Empyraeum.</hi> He ſuffered with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
and attended without deſpair, reſolved
to die, if God would have it ſo, or to live, if
he ſo ordained it. That which deceives men,
is, that they know not, or feign not to know,
that ſuffering ſerves as an infallible means unto
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:119982:90"/>
Heaven to pull us from the earth. It is that
ſecret which we ought to make the ſolid foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation
of our comfort, in all the accidents
that encounter us. Who can complain of his
miſeries, if he look upon them as the favours
of a goodneſſe, who regards but the advantage
of thoſe whom he ſeems to afflict?</p>
            <p>This Providence which holds the principal
part of this illuſtrious Comedy, furniſheth us
with fair reflections againſt our murmurers. For
laſtly, my Reader, if we will call to mind that
there never arriveth unto us any thing which is
not known to that wiſdome who hath no leſſe
power and goodneſſe to turn aſide our misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes,
then light to foreſee them, ſhould we be
ſo unreaſonable as to accuſe him of ſeveritie?
There is this notable difference of the love of
God, and that of men, that this latter cannot
be produced but in the communication of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits,
whereas the former hath not a more evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
teſtimonie of its tenderneſſe, then the
cruelty that it exerciſeth. It is not for us to
do evil, with intention to draw good from
thence, becauſe we have not the skill to make
our malice ſucceed with ſo much good fortune.
There is none but God who knowes this arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,
and who ought to ſerve himſelf there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with:
he doth it ordinarily both to ſeparate
us from the creatures, and to unite us to him.
Keep we firm in this principle. God knows
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:119982:91"/>
the means to ſave me, when he ſeems to deſtroy
me; let him diſpoſe of my life, and of my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune,
as it ſhall pleaſe him, I can never mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure,
becauſe I can never doubt of his power
and of his wiſdome, much leſſe of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe we notwithſtanding that this high
Majeſty hath not that induſtry to change the
things ſo contrary, and that it would not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct
us unto happineſs through miſery, nor un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
glory through infamy. We muſt remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
that God is the Soveraign of his creature,
and therefore it is ſubject unto all the uſes that
it ſhall pleaſe him. An Artificer hath much
right to ruine the work of his hand; he can if
he will burn the houſe which he hath built,
confound the image which he hath drawn,
break the pot which he hath moulded, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally
deſtroy all that which he hath made, by
this only reaſon, that he is the maſter thereof,
and the workman. Let us examine the rights
of our God, and we ſhall find that our nullity
cannot exceed his power. He hath not only gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
us the exteriour and the figure, which
bounds and which limits all the induſtry of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
maſters, but alſo his hand paſſeth even to
the bottome of our being, and makes the moſt
interiour of our ſubſtance. What law have we
to oblige him to our conſervation? What ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice
have we rendred to him to conſtrain him
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:119982:91"/>
to chuſe us the fortunes and conditions that
pleaſe us? The leaſt of our crimes may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
from his juſtice all the rigour of his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er;
but the greateſt of our homages cannot
merit the leaſt of his favours. Why then would
we force him to do us good, ſince we are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
culpable, and he is never debtor? Truly
his power ſhould be very much limited, if he
could not ſerve himſelf of us, but as we ſhould
think fit. The Maſter of all nature, he ſhould
become the ſlave of all men, ſince there is not
one of them content with his fortune, nor
modeſt in his ambitions. Whatſoever God
makes of us, let us acquieſce in his Providence:
he is juſt, if he ordain us puniſhment; he is
magnifick, if he doth us good.</p>
            <p>Let us look upon <hi>Joſeph</hi> in the chains, and
under the irons of a rude captivity, he retains
there a countenance ſo cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt, as if he were
upon the Arch of the Firmament; the Angels
are not more reſigned to the glory which they
poſſeſſe, then this innocent young man was to
the miſeries which he ſuffered. In which, not
to diſſemble, his vertue ſurpaſſed theirs much,
ſince there muſt be courage to bear evil, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
it is ſufficient to love for to conſent to his
good. What marvel is it that a Seraphim is
not diſtaſted with God amidſt the torrent of
eternal delights! What miracle, that a poor
creature is not troubled in the bitterneſſes of
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:119982:92"/>
a cruel fortune! it would not be much if the
juſt diſpute not glory but with the bleſſed ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,
it ſeems even that he carries it above his
God; that high Majeſty boaſts himſelf for
being deſcended into the priſons into the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany
of that holy Patriarch, and not to have
abandoned him in his chains. Truly his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcence
proves his goodneſſe, it expoſeth ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe
nothing of his intereſt; his pity
may comfort our miſery, but it cannot feel it;
and though it ſhould be true, that God were
ſenſible of evil (which we cannot think) he
would have always many aſſiſtances and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours,
which are needful to our nature. He is
puiſſant, we are weak; he is ſtrong, we are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm;
he is invariable, we are inconſtant; laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
he is God, and we are creatures. His pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
props him, our weakneſſe ſhakes us; his force
retains him, our infirmitie thruſts us off, his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutability
ſtaies him, our inconſtancy over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throws
us. It is then more glory to ſuffer as
man, then to compaſſionate as God, and it is
more to <hi>Joſeph</hi> who conſumed himſelf in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction,
then to his amiable Maſter who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held
him. Let us confeſſe that it is a great and
noble motive to fortifie us in our pains, to
know that we have a God, who deſpiſeth not
our miſeries, and who keeps to our chain. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca</hi>
aſſures, that his <hi>Jupiter</hi> ſees nothing but
the flat in parallel to the ſuffering of a good
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:119982:92"/>
man, yea, but he remains in the Heaven, and
participates not of his griefs but by the ſight.
He whom we adore, deſcends unto the Earth,
and enters into our priſons, not to be there ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctatour
of our combats, but to ſerve us for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond.
It is an illuſtrious duel, that of God
and man, againſt impatience and fortune; who
would be ſo cowardly to fly, when he ſhould
triumph? I come again notwithſtanding to
that which is ſweet in our Hiſtory; he who
tries us by afflictions, ſuſtains us by hope; he
never thruſts men into the liſts, but he hath
the buckler on his arm to defend him, and the
lawrels in his hand to crown him. My dear
Reader, if thou fighteſt, look well about thee;
and I aſſure thee, that thou ſhalt ſee her who
obſerves thy fidelity, and who prepares thy
reward; if thou demandeſt who it is, I anſwer,
it is the <hi>Divine Providence.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
